{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following writers has called Akbar's Din-i-Ilahi as a monument of his folly, not of wisdom?",
            "optionA": "  Badayuni ",
            "optionB": "  Vincent Smith ",
            "optionC": "  Barni ",
            "optionD": "  W.Haig ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVincent Arthur Smith was a British Indologist and art historian, who stated that Akbar's Din-i-Ilahi was a monument of his folly, not of wisdom\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "619932s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar's concept of Sulh-i-kul (or Qul) means",
            "optionA": "  friendship and goodwill to all ",
            "optionB": "  common brotherhood ",
            "optionC": "  fraternity and friendship ",
            "optionD": "  harmony and peace to all ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSulh-i kul is an Arabic term literally meaning \u201cpeace with all,\u201d \u201cuniversal peace,\u201d or \u201cabsolute peace,\u201d drawn from a Sufi mystic principle. As applied by the third Mughal Emperor of India, Akbar (who reigned 1556-1605), it described a peaceful and harmonious relationship among different religions. ",
            "keyString": "619968s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following buildings at Fatehpur Sikri is known as Ibadatkhana where Akbar used to hold religious discussions?",
            "optionA": "  Diwan-i-Aam ",
            "optionB": "  Diwan-i-Khas ",
            "optionC": "  Panch Mahal ",
            "optionD": "  Jami Masjid ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Diwan-i-Khas, or Hall of Private Audiences, in the Red Fort of Delhi built in 1571 was the place where the Mughal emperor Akbar received courtiers and state guests. It was also known as the Shah Mahal. ",
            "keyString": "619984s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hemu was captured and brought before Akbar by__________",
            "optionA": "  Bairam Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Salim ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Qulihan Mehran ",
            "optionD": "  Farid ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemu was captured and brought before Akbar by Shah Qulihan Mehran. ",
            "keyString": "619998s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Baz Bahadur was a . . . . . . in the court of Akbar",
            "optionA": "  Musician ",
            "optionB": "  Painter ",
            "optionC": "  Architect ",
            "optionD": "  Soldier ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaz Bahadur famous musician of Akbar\u2019s time, was made Manashba of 2000 by Akbar, the ruler of Malva. Abul Fazl wrote about him \u2013 \u201che was the best person of his time in music and Hindi songs.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "620009s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had built the 'Amber Fort'?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Man Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Uday Singh-II ",
            "optionD": "  Maharana Pratap ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Amber fort was built by Raja Man Singh in the 16th century and was completed by Sawai Jai Singh in the 18th Century. ",
            "keyString": "646777s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following towns is \"Moti Masjid\" situated?",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Moti Masjid (translation: Pearl Mosque) in Agra was built by Shah Jahan. During the rule of Shah Jahan the Mughal emperor, numerous architectural wonders were built, the most famous of them being the Taj Mahal. ",
            "keyString": "646826s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur summoned the pupils of the famous architect Sinan from",
            "optionA": "  Constantinople ",
            "optionB": "  Kabul ",
            "optionC": "  Syria ",
            "optionD": "  Egypt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur found leisure to summon from Constantinople pupils of the famous Albanian architect, Sinan, who had designed many important buildings in the Ottoman Empire and set them to work on mosques and other architectural monuments commemorating his conquest of Hindustan. ",
            "keyString": "684335s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The dead body of Babur by his own choice lies\nburied in",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Farghana ",
            "optionC": "  Samarqand ",
            "optionD": "  Kabul ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Emperor Babur died in 1530. He was first buried at Aaram Bagh, Agra. Later his remains were moved to Bagh-e-Babur (Babur Gardevs),Kabul. ",
            "keyString": "684369s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Rajput General who bravely fought the Battle of Khanwa before losing to Babur",
            "optionA": "  Rana Man Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Jai Singh ",
            "optionC": "  Rana Sanga ",
            "optionD": "  Rana Pratap ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Khanwa was fought near the village of Khanwa, in Bharatpur District of Rajasthan, on March 16, 1527. It was fought between the invading forces of the first Mughal Emperor Babur and the Rajput forces led by Rana Sanga of Mewar, after the Battle of Panipat. ",
            "keyString": "684384s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year (in A.D) did Babur invaded India?",
            "optionA": "  1530 ",
            "optionB": "  1520 ",
            "optionC": "  1526 ",
            "optionD": "  1550 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur defeated Ibrahim Lodi at the First Battle of Panipat in 1526 AD and founded the Mughal empire. ",
            "keyString": "684397s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the battle of Panipat, Babur faced the armies of",
            "optionA": "  Jaichand ",
            "optionB": "  Hemu ",
            "optionC": "  Daulat khan ",
            "optionD": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Babur defeated Ibrahim Lodi in the First Battle of Panipat (AD 1526). This marked the end of the Delhi Sultanate and the beginning of the Mughal Empire. This was one of the earliest battles involving gunpowderfirearms and field artillery. ",
            "keyString": "684410s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Mughal King reign during the large scale famine in Gujarat and Deccan?",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the one hand we hear of several famines which caused untold sufferings and on the other hand we hear the Golden Age of Shah Jahan. ",
            "keyString": "730891s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The reputed musician duo, Tansen and Baiju Bawra, flourished during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaiju Bawra (Baijnath Mishra) he was the drupadh singer of Medieval period. Miyan Tansen was the Mystical court singer ofMughal emperor Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "730999s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal rule the finance minister was known as",
            "optionA": "  Vakil ",
            "optionB": "  Diwan ",
            "optionC": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionD": "  Amin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Mughal rule, the status of Diwan in the province was equal to the status of a modern day finance minister.His main responsibilities were collection of taxes on behalf of the emperor. ",
            "keyString": "731032s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is wrongly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Sena dynasty \u2014Founded by Vijaya Sena ",
            "optionB": "  Pala dynasty \u2014Founded by Gopala ",
            "optionC": "  Prathihara dynasty \u2014Founded by Bhoja ",
            "optionD": "  Rastrakuta dynasty \u2014Founded by Amogavarsha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDantidurga (735\u2013756 CE), also known as Dantivarman or Dantidurga II was the founder of the Rashtrakuta Empire of Manyakheta. ",
            "keyString": "731056s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Battle for Delhi was fought in the year __________",
            "optionA": "  1764 ",
            "optionB": "  1526 ",
            "optionC": "  1556 ",
            "optionD": "  1857 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Delhi also known as the battle of Tughlaqabad was fought between Hemu (the General of Adil Shah Suri) and the Mughal forces led by Tardi Beg Khan in the year 1556. Hemu won the battle and over took Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "731081s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Haldighati was fought between",
            "optionA": "  Akbar and Rana Sangram Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar and Medini Rai ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar and Rana Pratap Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar and Uday Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Haldighati was a battle fought on 18 June 1576 between cavalry and archers supporting the Rana of Mewar, Maharana Pratap, and the Mughal emperor Akbar's forces, led by Man Singh I of Amber.",
            "keyString": "774226s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following had shifted the capital of the Mughal empire from Agra to Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Mughal emperor to crown Agra as capital of mughal empire, was Akbar in the year 1526. The capital of mughal empire was changed from Agra to Delhi by Shah Jahan in the year 1638. ",
            "keyString": "774317s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In whose reign did the Mughal painting reach its zenith?",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jahangir's reign did the Mughal painting reach its zenith. ",
            "keyString": "774370s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was defended by Chand Bibi against the Mughals?",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Berar ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmednagar ",
            "optionD": "  Bedar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChand Bibi is best known for defending Ahmednagar against the Mughal forces of Emperor Akbar in 1595. ",
            "keyString": "774397s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A hearty welcome was extended to the English captain Hawkins by the Mughal Emperor",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA hearty welcome was extended to the English captain Hawkins by the Mughal Emperor Jahangir, and on this the Portuguese got angry. ",
            "keyString": "774427s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said the given statement - \"I came alone and I am going alone. I have not done well to the country and the people, and of the future there is no hope\"",
            "optionA": "  Mir Jumla ",
            "optionB": "  Dara Shikoh ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb said the given statement - \"I came alone and I am going alone. I have not done well to the country and the people, and of the future there is no hope\". ",
            "keyString": "839885s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Indian king who warmly received the Portuguese traveller Vasco da Gama when he landed at Calicut",
            "optionA": "  Asaf Jah Ismail Mulk ",
            "optionB": "  Devaraya ",
            "optionC": "  Zamorin ",
            "optionD": "  Krishnadevaraya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe king of Calicut, Zamorin welcomed Vasco-da-gama when he landed at calicut in 1498. ",
            "keyString": "840798s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following attacked the Somnath temple?",
            "optionA": "  Mahmud of Ghazni ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Ghori ",
            "optionC": "  Iltutmish ",
            "optionD": "  Qutb-ud-din Aibak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe prominent Turkic ruler Mahmud of Ghazni raided Gujarat, plundering the Somnath temple and breaking its jyotirlinga despite pleas by Brahmins not to break it. He took away a booty of 20 million dinars. ",
            "keyString": "841483s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the language that was designated as the 'Camp Language' during the Medieval Period",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Pali ",
            "optionC": "  Hindi ",
            "optionD": "  Urdu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUrdu was designated the camp language of Medieval India. The word Urdu is a Turkish word that means military camp 'a Lashkar'. Urdu language was developed due to contact of Hindu, Turkish and Afghan soldiers. ",
            "keyString": "842074s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Mughal Emperors was half Rajput?",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan & Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar Jahan & Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Jahan & Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir & Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJahangir was half-Rajput and quarter-Persian, and Shah Jahan was three-quarters Rajput. ",
            "keyString": "842638s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the only women historian to have written a historical account of Mughal Period?",
            "optionA": "  Noorjahan Begum ",
            "optionB": "  Zebun-nissa Begum ",
            "optionC": "  Gulbadan Begum ",
            "optionD": "  Jahanara Begum ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGulbadan Begum (1523-1603) was a Perso-Turkic Princess, the daughter of Emperor Babur. She is most known as the author of Humayun Nama, the account of the life of her brother, Humayun. ",
            "keyString": "943907s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals, in urban area the judicial powers were exercised by",
            "optionA": "  Kazis ",
            "optionB": "  Faujdar ",
            "optionC": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionD": "  Wazir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of king's powers in urban areas were exercised by the kotwal, a secular functionary of the police, responsible under the Mughals for the peace of cities and towns. ",
            "keyString": "944706s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chand Bibi was the ruler of",
            "optionA": "  Ahmednagar ",
            "optionB": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionC": "  Satara ",
            "optionD": "  Golconda ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChand Bibi (1550\u20131599 CE), was an Indian Muslim regent and warrior. She acted as the Regent of Bijapur (1580\u201390) and Regent of Ahmednagar (in current day Maharashtra) (1596\u201399). Chand Bibi is best known for defending Ahmednagar against the Mughal forces of Emperor Akbar in 1595. ",
            "keyString": "944931s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal emperor is credited with having composed secular Hindi songs?",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun ",
            "optionD": "  Babur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal emperor Jahangir is credited with having composed secular Hindi songs. ",
            "keyString": "945127s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who got construced 'Grand Trunk Road'?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Ashoka ",
            "optionC": "  Shershah Suri ",
            "optionD": "  Samudra Gupta ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Grand Trunk Road, built by Sher Shah Suri, a ruler of the Indian sub continent in the 16th century AD, starts in Kabul, Afghanistan. The road continues to Pakistan near Peshawar through the famous Khyber Pass. ",
            "keyString": "945305s28m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The East India Company was founded in India during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1612, James I instructed Sir Thomas Roe to visit the Mughal Emperor Nur-ud-din Salim Jahangir (r. 1605\u20131627) to arrange for a commercial treaty that would give the company exclusive rights to reside and establish factories in Surat and other areas. ",
            "keyString": "33009s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal Emperor who caused the murder of Guru Arjan was",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuru Arjan was arrested under the orders of the Mughal Emperor Jahangir and asked to convert to Islam. He refused, was tortured and executed in 1606 CE. Historical records and the Sikh tradition are unclear whether Guru Arjan was executed by drowning or died during torture. ",
            "keyString": "33059s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal Ruler's gave permission for collecting Chauth and Sardesh Mukhi on Maratha land to Peshwa Balaji Vishwanath?",
            "optionA": "  Farrukhsiyar ",
            "optionB": "  Rafi-ud-Darajat ",
            "optionC": "  Rafi-ud-Daula ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammed Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFarrukhsiyar gave permission for collecting Chauth and Sardesh Mukhi on Maratha land to Peshwa Balaji Vishwanath. ",
            "keyString": "33201s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two major crops introduced in India during the Mughal period were",
            "optionA": "  Millet and Groundnut ",
            "optionB": "  Potato and Mustard ",
            "optionC": "  Tobacco and Maize ",
            "optionD": "  Indigo and Maize ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo major crops introduced in India during the Mughal period were Tobacco and Maize. ",
            "keyString": "33303s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the battle of Haldighati fought?",
            "optionA": "  1776 ",
            "optionB": "  1676 ",
            "optionC": "  1576 ",
            "optionD": "  1476 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Haldighati was a battle fought on 18 June 1576 between cavalry and archers supporting the Rana of Mewar, Maharana Pratap; and the Mughal emperor Akbar's forces, led by Man Singh I of Amber.",
            "keyString": "33396s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following, with whom Akbar did not come into contact?",
            "optionA": "  Jains ",
            "optionB": "  Parsis ",
            "optionC": "  Buddhists ",
            "optionD": "  Christians ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar did not come into contact with Buddhist. ",
            "keyString": "114268s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the year 1582, Akbar took the momentous step of",
            "optionA": "  Banning Sati ",
            "optionB": "  Removing Jaziya ",
            "optionC": "  Forming an army of jackals ",
            "optionD": "  Propounding a new religion Din-i-Ilahi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Din-i Ilahi (lit. \"Religion of God\") was a syncretic religion propounded by the Mughal emperor Akbar in 1582 CE, intending to merge some of the elements of the religions of his empire, and thereby reconcile the differences that divided his subjects. ",
            "keyString": "114860s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hemu, whom Akbar defeated In the Second Battle of Panipat (1556), was",
            "optionA": "  Minister of Sikandar Shah Suri ",
            "optionB": "  Minister of Muhammad Adil Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Ruler of Rewari ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister of Rana Udai Singh of Mewar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Second Battle of Panipat was fought on November 5, 1556, between the forces of Hemu, the Hindu general and Chief Minister of Adil Shah Suri, and the army of the Mughal emperor, Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "115246s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mansabdari System was founded by Akbar. The Mansabdars were",
            "optionA": "  military commanders ",
            "optionB": "  provincial governors ",
            "optionC": "  high civil and military officers ",
            "optionD": "  all of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAppointment to the ranks of mansabdars was made by the emperor, usually on the recommendation of military leaders, provincial governors, or court officials. ",
            "keyString": "115566s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar had constructed several forts, which did not include the one of",
            "optionA": "  Lahore ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionD": "  Red Fort ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe fort is called Red Fort or Lal QiIa because it is made of red sandstone. The history of forts indicates that it was built between the year 1639-1648 by the Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan in old Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "115833s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where French established their first factory?",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Masaulipatam ",
            "optionC": "  Pulicat ",
            "optionD": "  Cochin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJean-Baptiste Colbert founded the French East India Company in 1664. The initial attempts of the company to found a successful colony on Madagascar got failed. In 1667, under Francis Caron, the company established first factory at Surat and second factory was established at Masulipattanam a year later. ",
            "keyString": "185735s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What do you mean by Mughal Zagir?",
            "optionA": "  Providing rent free land ",
            "optionB": "  Zamidar's property ",
            "optionC": "  Giving officer a right to revenue ",
            "optionD": "  Giving cash salary to Mansabdar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tZagirdari system was the system of giving an official right to collect revenue from a particular area called 'Zagir'.",
            "keyString": "185768s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal rule, the police duties in the districts were entrusted to the officials known as?",
            "optionA": "  Faujdar ",
            "optionB": "  Mansabdar ",
            "optionC": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionD": "  Amin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Mughal rule, the police duties in the districts were entrusted to the officials known as Faujdar. ",
            "keyString": "185783s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Mughal administration, military recruitment had been looked after by the",
            "optionA": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionB": "  Bakhshi ",
            "optionC": "  Wazir ",
            "optionD": "  Diwan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Mughal administration, military recruitment had been looked after by the Bakhshi. ",
            "keyString": "185795s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Mughal emperors is credited with composition of Hindi songs?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Emperor Jahangir had a keen interest in music. He also composed few hindi songs. Jahangir, the Mughal Emperor, is credited with the composition of many Hindi songs. ",
            "keyString": "185806s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Akbar's Gold Mohur bore the figures of Sita and Ram\nII. Akbar's Gold Mohur bore the image of Prophet Mohammad\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct related to the Akbar reign?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ram Siya coin issued by Mughal Emperor Akbar in 1604-05. It has the image of Ram and Sita on one side with the word Ram and Siya written above in Devnagri script. Ram is shown holding a bow and arrow while Sita has lotus in both her hands. ",
            "keyString": "243063s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To whom did Akbar gave the title Mian?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Todar Mal ",
            "optionB": "  Man Singh-I ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal ",
            "optionD": "  Tansen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar considered him as a Navaratnas (nine jewels), and gave him the title Mian, an honorific, meaning learned man. Tansen was a composer, musician and vocalist, to whom a large number of compositions have been attributed in northern regions of the Indian subcontinent. ",
            "keyString": "243181s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mansabdari system introduced by Akbar was borrowed from the system prevalent in",
            "optionA": "  Persia ",
            "optionB": "  Mongolia ",
            "optionC": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionD": "  Turkey ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMansabdar implies the generic term for the military-kind grading of all royal functionaries of the Mughal Empire. The Mansabdari system introduced by Akbar was borrowed from the system followed in Mongolia. ",
            "keyString": "243218s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Akbar's reign the Mahabharat was translated into Persian and is known as",
            "optionA": "  Iqbal Nama ",
            "optionB": "  Razm Nama ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar Nama ",
            "optionD": "  Sakinat-ul-Auliya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"Razmnama\"(war Tab) is the persian translation of the Mahabharta. Preface of this book was written by the Akbar's, court poet Abul Fazal. ",
            "keyString": "243249s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar founded the Din-i-Ilahi primarily to",
            "optionA": "  Establish a national religion which would be acceptable to the Muslims and the Hindus ",
            "optionB": "  Ensure racial and communal harmony ",
            "optionC": "  Found a religious institution ",
            "optionD": "  Put an end to differences between Hindus and Muslims ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of Akbar's most unusual ideas regarding religion was Din-i-Ilahi (\u201cGodism\u201d in English), which was an eclectic mix of Hinduism, Islam, and Christianity. ",
            "keyString": "243285s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rana Pratap Singh of Mewar was defeated by the Mughal army in the battle of",
            "optionA": "  Mewar ",
            "optionB": "  Chittor ",
            "optionC": "  Haldighati ",
            "optionD": "  Udaipur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Haldighati was a battle fought on 18 June 1576 between cavalry and archers supporting the Rana of Mewar, Maharana Pratap; and the Mughal emperor Akbar's forces, led by Man Singh I of Amber. After a fierce battle lasting more than three hours, Pratap found himself wounded and the day lost. ",
            "keyString": "325835s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughals imported fruits from",
            "optionA": "  Samarkand ",
            "optionB": "  Arabia ",
            "optionC": "  Kabul ",
            "optionD": "  Portugal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur, the first Mughal emperor, was raised on a Central Asian diet that placed tremendous emphasis on the many fruits that passed through the region. In the markets of Samarkand one could purchase sweet apples, lush melons, and a bounty of other fruits from the region's orchards. ",
            "keyString": "325950s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal emperor who had died owing to a sudden fall from the staircase was",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal Emperor Humayun died after a sudden fall from the stairs of his library in his fort at Delhi in 1556 AD. ",
            "keyString": "325984s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Permission to the British to establish their trading centre at Surat had been given by the Mughal emperor",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSir Thomas Roe from company reached the court of the Mughal Emperor, Jahangir, as the emissary of King James I in 1615, and gained for the British the right to establish a factory at Surat. ",
            "keyString": "326006s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the Pala ruler who was the first to plunge into the tripartite struggle",
            "optionA": "  Devapala ",
            "optionB": "  Mahipala ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmapala ",
            "optionD": "  Gopala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGopala of the Pala dynasty was the first to plunge into the tripartite struggle. ",
            "keyString": "326040s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During whose reign did William Hawkins visit the Mughal court to secure a right. to trade in Mughal ports?",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Jahangir's reign did William Hawkins visit the Mughal court to secure a right. to trade in Mughal ports. ",
            "keyString": "424579s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sawai Raja Jai Singh was the ruler of __________",
            "optionA": "  Amber ",
            "optionB": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionC": "  Satara ",
            "optionD": "  Kannauj ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharaja Sawai Jai Singh (3 November 1688 \u2013 21 September 1743) was the Hindu Rajput ruler of the kingdom of Amber (later called Jaipur). He was born at Amber, the capital of the Kachwahas. He became ruler of Amber at the age of 11 after his father Maharaja Bishan Singh died on 31 December 1699. ",
            "keyString": "424613s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal architecture attained unrivalled magnificence during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal architecture reached its zenith during the reign of Shah Jahan, who constructed the Taj Mahal, the Jama Masjid, the Red Fort, and the Shalimar Gardens in Lahore. ",
            "keyString": "424628s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who got the Gita translated into Persian?",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Murad ",
            "optionD": "  Dara Shikoh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSo'aal o Jawaab bain-e-Laal Daas wa Dara Shikoh (also called Mukaalama-i Baba Laal Daas wa Dara Shikoh) Sirr-e-Akbar (The Great Secret, his translation of the Upanishads in Persian) Persian translations of the Yoga Vasishta and Bhagavad Gita. ",
            "keyString": "424640s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal School of Painting was interested in portraying",
            "optionA": "  Mughal court ",
            "optionB": "  Domestic subjects ",
            "optionC": "  Scenes from the Indian classics ",
            "optionD": "  The scenes of their motherland ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal painting remained confined to the Mughal court and did not reach the people.",
            "keyString": "424652s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the last 25 years of his reign, Aurangzeb was mainly involved in long-drawn wars against",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Golcunda ",
            "optionC": "  Marathas ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the last 25 years of his reign, Aurangzeb was mainly involved in long-drawn wars against Marathas. ",
            "keyString": "473448s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements are correct regarding Aurangzeb?\nI. He forbade the cultivation of Bhang\nII. Forbade singing at court\nIII. A proficient player of Veena\nIV. His tomb is at Tughlaqabad",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb forbaded the cultivation of Bhang. He forbaded singing at court and a proficient player of Veena. ",
            "keyString": "473523s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Koh-i-noor diamond was presented to Aurangzeb by",
            "optionA": "  Mirkasim ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Jumla ",
            "optionC": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMir Jumla (1591-1663) a nobleman in the service of the State of Golkonda in the Deccan plateau of Central India was the first owner of what was later known as the Kohinoor then the largest diamond in the world. Mir Jumla was a Persian born near Isfahan in Iran. He was the son of an oil merchant. Koh-i-noor diamond was presented to Aurangzeb by him. ",
            "keyString": "473544s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Aurangzeb died?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangabad ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmednagar ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Mughal Emperor Aurangzeb died at the age of 88 in Ahmednagar in 1707. He died due to terminal illness. ",
            "keyString": "473557s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb came to power after winning the war of succession and by defeating his three brothers",
            "optionA": "  Dara ",
            "optionB": "  Shuja ",
            "optionC": "  Askari ",
            "optionD": "  Murad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb came to power after winning the war of succession and by defeating his three brothers Askari. ",
            "keyString": "473571s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the second Anglo-Mysore War fought?",
            "optionA": "  1780-84 ",
            "optionB": "  1788-89 ",
            "optionC": "  1784-88 ",
            "optionD": "  1770-74 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Second Anglo\u2013Mysore War was a conflict between the Kingdom of Mysore and the British East India Company from 1780 to 1784. ",
            "keyString": "547682s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. His reign saw beginning of a new intercourse between Europe of India\nII. Attempted to prohibit traffic in eunuchs\nIII. Started practices of inter-caste marriages between the families of government officers\nIV. Ordered the abolition of inhuman corporal punishments\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct related to Jahangir?",
            "optionA": "  I, II, and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II, and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, III, and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHis reign saw beginning of a new intercourse between Europe of India. He attempted to prohibit traffic in eunuchs. He ordered the abolition of inhuman corporal punishments. ",
            "keyString": "547718s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Jahangir had set up his court at Allahabad, assumed royal titles and struck coins in his name\nII. He banned slaughter of animals on two days in every week viz - Sunday & Thursday.\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct related to Jahangir?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJahangir had set up his court at Allahabad, assumed royal titles and struck coins in his name. He banned slaughter of animals on two days in every week viz - Sunday & Thursday. ",
            "keyString": "547741s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. The full name of Jahangir was Nuruddin Md. Jahangir\nII. Jahangir had ended a long drawn out struggle with Mewar\nIII. Mahabat Khan revolted against Jahangir and captured Jahangir and his wife Nurjahan at Lahore\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct related to Jahangir?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe full name of Jahangir was Nuruddin Md. Jahangir. Jahangir had ended a long drawn out struggle with Mewar. Mahabat Khan revolted against Jahangir and captured Jahangir and his wife Nurjahan at Lahore.",
            "keyString": "547759s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the architect who designed \"Taj Mahal\" ?",
            "optionA": "  Muhammad Hussain ",
            "optionB": "  Ustad Ahmed Lahori ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Isa ",
            "optionD": "  Ismail ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUstad Ahmad Lahori, also spelled as 'Ahmad Lahori' was an Iranian architect. He is said to have been chief architect of the Taj Mahal in Agra, India, built between 1632 and 1648 during the ruling period of Mughal emperor Shah Jahan. ",
            "keyString": "547775s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important political gain to the Mughals during the reign of Shah Jahan was",
            "optionA": "  annexation of Ahmadnagar ",
            "optionB": "  treaties with Bijapur and Golcunda ",
            "optionC": "  both (A) and (B) above ",
            "optionD": "  expulsion of the Portuguese from Hughli ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJahangir gave the title of Shah Jahan to prince Khurram at that very time. But it was, in fact, no remarkable success of the Mughals. Ahmadnagar was not prepared to accept the sovereignty of the Mughals and started fighting against them again. However, peace was again signed between the two in 1621 A.D. by which Ahmadnagar surrendered a part of its territory to the Mughals and also paid rupees eighteen lakhs in cash. Bijapur and Golkunda which had helped Ahmadnagar also paid rupees twelve lakhs and rupees twenty lakhs respectively to the Mughals. Thus, during the reign of Jahangir, Ahmadnagar was weakened and the states of Bijapur and Golkunda were pressurised. ",
            "keyString": "597641s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sher Shah defeated Humayun at",
            "optionA": "  Gaur ",
            "optionB": "  Chunar ",
            "optionC": "  Chausa ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Chausa was a notable military engagement between the Mughal emperor, Humayun, and the Afghan, Sher Shah Suri. It was fought on 26 June 1539 at Chausa, 10 miles southwest of Buxar in modern-day Bihar, India. Sher Shah was victorious and crowned himself Far\u012bd al-D\u012bn Sh\u0113r Shah. ",
            "keyString": "597804s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun lost the Mughal Empire to Sher Shah Suri finally in the battle of",
            "optionA": "  Chunar ",
            "optionB": "  Chausa ",
            "optionC": "  Ghagra ",
            "optionD": "  Kannauj ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 26 June 1539, Sher Khan faced Humayun in the Battle of Chausa and defeated him. Assuming the title Farid al-D\u012bn Sher Shah, he defeated Humayun once again at Kannauj in May 1540 and forced him out of India. ",
            "keyString": "597841s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are correct regarding Shahjahan?\nI. Ousted the Portuguese from Hugli\nII. Created the office of Amin for assessment of revenue\nIII. Kahabat Khan was appointed governor of Lahore\nIV. Ali Mardan Khan surrendered Kandhar to Mughals",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShahjahan ousted the Portuguese from Hugli. He created the office of Amin for assessment of revenue. Ali Mardan Khan surrendered Kandhar to Mughals. ",
            "keyString": "597861s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) related to the Dara Shikoh\nI. Dara Shikoh was the youngest son of Shahjahan.\nII. Dara Shikoh was the devotee of Qadiri Silsila.",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II are incorrect ",
            "optionC": "  Only I is correct ",
            "optionD": "  Only II is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDara Shukoh was a follower of the Persian \"perennialist\" mystic Sarmad Kashani, as well as Lahore's famous Qadiri Sufi saint Hazrat Mian Mir, whom he was introduced to by Mullah Shah Badakhshi (Mian Mir's spiritual disciple and successor). ",
            "keyString": "597884s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Inam land was one which was assigned to",
            "optionA": "  Scholars and religious persons ",
            "optionB": "  Mansabdars ",
            "optionC": "  Hereditary revenue collectors ",
            "optionD": "  Nobles ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Nizam Rub, the ruler used to give 'inam' (gift of land or land revenue) to scholar and religions person who served them. ",
            "keyString": "643923s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All the early Mughal Emperors except __________ were great builders",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the early Mughal Emperors except Aurangzeb were great builders. ",
            "keyString": "644056s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Noor Jahan was wife of which Mughal Emperor?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNur Jahan (born Mehr-un-Nissa) (31 May 1577 \u2013 17 December 1645) was the twentieth (and last) wife of the Mughal emperor Jahangir. ",
            "keyString": "644131s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What does Jahangir mean?",
            "optionA": "  National Monarach ",
            "optionB": "  The Grand Monarch ",
            "optionC": "  Conqueror of the world ",
            "optionD": "  Hero of hundred battles ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Prince Salim was the eldest son of Emperor, Akbar. He took the imperial (reign) name 'Jahangir' which means conqueror of the world. ",
            "keyString": "644189s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who built Red Fort?",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstructed in 1639 by the fifth Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan as the palace of his fortified capital Shahjahanabad, the Red Fort is named for its massive enclosing walls of red sandstone and is adjacent to the older Salimgarh Fort, built by Islam Shah Suri in 1546 AD. ",
            "keyString": "644231s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur was born in the year",
            "optionA": "  1483 ",
            "optionB": "  1583 ",
            "optionC": "  1693 ",
            "optionD": "  1783 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur (14 February 1483 \u2013 26 December 1530), born Zahir ud-Din Muhammad, was the founder and first Emperor of the Mughal dynasty in India. ",
            "keyString": "688608s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur came to India originally from",
            "optionA": "  Khiva ",
            "optionB": "  Ferghana ",
            "optionC": "  Khorasan ",
            "optionD": "  Seistan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tZahiruddin Muhammad was born on February 14, 1483 in the town of Andijan, in the Fergana Valley which is in modern Uzbekistan. ",
            "keyString": "688645s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur (1526-1530 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Mughal ",
            "optionB": "  Nanda ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Haryanka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal Empire was founded by Babur (reigned 1526\u20131530), a Central Asian ruler who was descended from the Turco-Mongol conqueror Timur (the founder of the Timurid Empire) on his father's side and from Chagatai, the second son of the Mongol ruler Genghis Khan, on his mother's side. ",
            "keyString": "688662s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur was succeeded to the Mughal throne by",
            "optionA": "  Sher Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun ",
            "optionD": "  Bhadur Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur married several times. Notable among his sons are Humayun, Kamran Mirza and Hindal Mirza. Babur died in 1530 in Agra and was succeeded by Humayun. ",
            "keyString": "688685s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal leader Babur originally invaded northern India",
            "optionA": "  To creates a Shiite Muslim state ",
            "optionB": "  Because he was unable to achieve his ambitious goals in central Asia ",
            "optionC": "  To control the trade routes into Southeast Asia ",
            "optionD": "  To defeat his longstanding enemy, the sultan of Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal leader Babur originally invaded northern India because he was unable to achieve his ambitious goals in central Asia. ",
            "keyString": "688699s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was sent as an ambassador to the royal court of Jahangir by James I, the king of England?",
            "optionA": "  John Hawkins ",
            "optionB": "  Willia Todd ",
            "optionC": "  Sir Thomas Roe ",
            "optionD": "  Sir Walter Raleigh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1614, Roe was elected Member of Parliament for Tamworth. From 1615 to 1618, he was ambassador to the court at Agra, India, of the Great Mughal Ruler, Jahangir. His journal was a valuable source of information for the reign of Jahangir. ",
            "keyString": "731106s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughal rule the judicial service was formed by",
            "optionA": "  Vakil ",
            "optionB": "  Diwan ",
            "optionC": "  Kazis ",
            "optionD": "  Mansabdars ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mughal rule the judicial service was formed by Kazis. ",
            "keyString": "731147s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The city of Dhillika (Delhi) was founded by the",
            "optionA": "  Chauhans ",
            "optionB": "  Tomars ",
            "optionC": "  Pawars ",
            "optionD": "  Pariharas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi has a long history and is known to be the city called Indraprastha during the epic times. But historically Delhi's name is associated with a Tomar King named Anangpal, who founded the Red Fort (Lal Kot) in the middle of the 11th century. ",
            "keyString": "731170s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about Sudarshan Lake. Which of them is correct?",
            "optionA": "  It was constructed by Pushyagupta, the Governor of Saurashtra region during Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Tushaap constructed a darn on the lake during Ashoka Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  First reconstruction was undertaken by Governor Suvishakh during Saka satrap Rudradaman and 2nd by Chakrapalit during the reign of Skandgupta ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSudarshan Lake was constructed by Pushyagupta, the Governor of Saurashtra region during Chandragupta Maurya. Tushaap constructed a darn on the lake during Ashoka Maurya. First reconstruction was undertaken by Governor Suvishakh during Saka satrap Rudradaman and 2nd by Chakrapalit during the reign of Skandgupta. ",
            "keyString": "731188s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following fort was known as the 'Key of Deccan'?",
            "optionA": "  Kalinjar ",
            "optionB": "  Ajaygarh ",
            "optionC": "  Asirgarh ",
            "optionD": "  Gulbarga ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAsirgarh fort was built by Muslim emperor Asa Ahir in the peak of the Satpura Ranges, Madhya Pradesh. It is also known as 'Babe Deccan' which means \"Key to the Deccan and also Door to South India\". ",
            "keyString": "731206s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Mughal Garden in India had been laid out by",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe founder of the Mughal empire, Babur, described his favourite type of garden as a charbagh. They use the term bagh, baug, bageecha or bagicha for garden. ",
            "keyString": "772781s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughal rule the main occupation of the people was",
            "optionA": "  Sea faring ",
            "optionB": "  Agriculture  ",
            "optionC": "  Working in mines ",
            "optionD": "  Service in the army ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian agricultural production increased under the Mughal Empire. A variety of crops were grown, including food crops such as wheat, rice, and barley, and non-food cash crops such as cotton, indigo and opium. ",
            "keyString": "772815s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct about Portuguese?",
            "optionA": "  They brought tobacco cultivation in India ",
            "optionB": "  They spread Catholicism in western and eastern coast of India ",
            "optionC": "  They established first printing press in India at Goa in AD 1556 ",
            "optionD": "  The Indian Medicinal Plants was the first scientific work which was published at Andhra Pradesh in 1563 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Portuguese were the first Europeans to write scientifically on plants and especially on medicinal plants. Garcia da Orta who published his work Coloquios dos Simples e Drogas da India in 1563 from Goa is considered the pioneer in this field.",
            "keyString": "772830s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Upanishads were translated by Dara Shikoh in Persian under the title of",
            "optionA": "  Mayma-ul-Bahrain ",
            "optionB": "  Sirr-i-Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Al-Fihrist ",
            "optionD": "  Kitabul Bayan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSo'aal o Jawaab bain-e-Laal Daas wa Dara Shikoh (also called Mukaalama-i Baba Laal Daas wa Dara Shikoh) Sirr-e-Akbar (The Great Secret, his translation of the Upanishads in Persian) Persian translations of the Yoga Vasishta and Bhagavad Gita. ",
            "keyString": "772843s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement (s) is/are correct related to Mughal's decline?\nI. Mughal's noble were well known for their loyalty but war of successor degenerated the nobility led to the decline of Mughal.\nII. Mughal Empire declined due to over decentralization of administration.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I and II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProlong war of succession fractured the administrative unit of Mughal\u2019s. Weakness of the Nobility: Mughal\u2019s noble were well known for their loyalty but war of successor degenerated the nobility. The mighty Mughal Empire began to decline after the death of Aurangzeb. The declining prospect of Mughal rule was knelled by quick succession and also war of succession. ",
            "keyString": "772855s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the second capital of Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Fatehpur Sikri ",
            "optionD": "  Patna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Akbar's Victory over Rajputana of Chittor and Ranthambor, he shifted his capital from Agra to a new city which he named 'Fatehpur Sikri' (the city of victory). ",
            "keyString": "847001s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The innovator of the Revenue settlement during the rule of Akbar was",
            "optionA": "  Raja Mansingh ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Bhagwan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Todarmal ",
            "optionD": "  Raja Birbal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Todar Mal was the Finance Minister of the Mughal empire during Akbar's reign. Todarmal was the chief finance minister (Diwan-e-kul) of Mughal Emperor Akbar. He introduced many land revenue reforms like land measurement reforms, Dhasala system and Karoni system. ",
            "keyString": "847035s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar saw the sea for the first time in his life at",
            "optionA": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Surat ",
            "optionC": "  Cambay ",
            "optionD": "  Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt Cambay, Akbar saw the sea for the first time and rode on it in a boat. ",
            "keyString": "847050s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The medieval Hindu ruler who was a contemporary of Akbar, and took the title of Vikramaditya was",
            "optionA": "  Rana Pratap (of Mewar) ",
            "optionB": "  Sadasiva Raya (of Vijayanagar) ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Man Singh (of Amber) ",
            "optionD": "  Hemachandra (Hemu) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe medieval Hindu ruler who was a contemporary of Akbar, and took the title of Vikramaditya was Hemachandra (Hemu). Hemu claimed royal status after defeating Akbar's Mughal forces on 7 October 1556 in the Battle of Delhi and assumed the ancient title of Vikramaditya that had been adopted by many Hindu kings in the past. A month later, Hemu was wounded by a chance arrow and captured during the Second Battle of Panipat. ",
            "keyString": "847063s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar had got constructed the Buland Darwaza to commemorate his victory of",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuland Darwaza, or the \"Gate of victory\", was built in 1572 A.D. by Mughal emperor Akbar to commemorate his victory over Gujarat. It is the main entrance to the palace at Fatehpur Sikri, which is 43 km from Agra, India. ",
            "keyString": "847074s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has completed the annexation of Ahmednagar?",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhan Jahan Lodi had sold off Balaghat to Ahmadnagar just before the accession of Shah Jahan on the throne. When he revolted, he found shelter in Ahmadnagar. Shah Jahan sent a strong force against Khan Jahan and Ahmadnagar in 1629 A.D. Ahmadnagar, withdrew its support to Khan Jahan but refused to submit itself. The Mughuls could succeed only partially against it. ",
            "keyString": "884322s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal Emperor fought the battle of Panipat in 1526?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Battle of Panipat was fought between the invading forces of Babur and the Lodi Empire, which took place on 21 April 1526 in North India. It marked the beginning of the Mughal Empire. ",
            "keyString": "884355s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find out the correct match of the following",
            "optionA": "  Asaf Khan - Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Adam Khan - Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Bairam Khan - Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shaista Khan - Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBairam Khan was the most prominet military commander-in-chief of the Mughal Army. He was the Guardian, mentor and the teacher of emperor Arkbar. ",
            "keyString": "924218s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals the cotton goods were exported to",
            "optionA": "  Africa ",
            "optionB": "  Sumatra ",
            "optionC": "  Japan ",
            "optionD": "  England ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mughals the main markets was of cotton goods, India's chief export product exported to Africa. ",
            "keyString": "924252s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who discovered a direct sea route to India?",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Germans ",
            "optionC": "  The French ",
            "optionD": "  The Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe discovery of the sea route to India is the description sometimes used in Europe and among the Portuguese for the first recorded trip made directly from Europe to India via the Atlantic Ocean. It was undertaken under the command of Portuguese explorer Vasco da Gama during the reign of King Manuel I in 1497\u20131499. ",
            "keyString": "924266s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Slaves who were in great demand under the Mughals were",
            "optionA": "  Abyssinians ",
            "optionB": "  Persians ",
            "optionC": "  Africans ",
            "optionD": "  Afghans ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn extensive demand for slaves was created within India, the demand coming from Mughals. The considerable imports of Abyssinian slaves were in great demand. ",
            "keyString": "924279s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who are credited to a large extent for ending the Mughal rule in India?",
            "optionA": "  Mauryas ",
            "optionB": "  Cholas ",
            "optionC": "  Guptas ",
            "optionD": "  Marathas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Marathas especially the great maratha rulers Chattrapati Shivaji, Sambhaji, Tarabai and Peshwa Bajirao-I are credited to a large extent for ending the Mughal rule in India.",
            "keyString": "924291s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar's nurse-in-chief was",
            "optionA": "  Mumtaj ",
            "optionB": "  Hamida Begum ",
            "optionC": "  Jahanara ",
            "optionD": "  Maham Anaga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaham Anga was Akbar's chief nurse prior to his enthronement at age thirteen as Mughal emperor in 1556. ",
            "keyString": "962218s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main outlet for foreign trade during Akbar's reign was the port of",
            "optionA": "  Karachi ",
            "optionB": "  Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Surat ",
            "optionD": "  Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring his reign they were the most powerful at sea. Trade at Surat, the main port of Mughal India. Gujarat that emerged as the leading outlet at a given time. ",
            "keyString": "962257s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar's teacher was",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionB": "  Bairam Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Abdul Latif ",
            "optionD": "  Kabir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar was very tolerant in his religious views. In his childhood he was impressed by the liberal religious ideas of his teacher, Abdul Latif. ",
            "keyString": "962274s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The original name of Tansen, the greatest musician of the court of Akbar, was",
            "optionA": "  Makaranda Pandey ",
            "optionB": "  Ramatanu Pande ",
            "optionC": "  Haridas ",
            "optionD": "  Lal Kalawant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTansen (c. 1500 \u2013 1586), also referred to as Tan Sen or Ramtanu Pandey, was a prominent figure of North Indian (Hindustani) classical music. Born in a Hindu family, he learned and perfected his art in the northwest region of modern Madhya Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "962288s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar (1556-1605 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Maurya ",
            "optionC": "  Mughal ",
            "optionD": "  Haryanka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbu'l-Fath Jalal-ud-din Muhammad Akbar (October 1542\u2013 27 October 1605), popularly known as Akbar I, also as Akbar the Great (Akbar-i-azam), was the third Mughal emperor, who reigned from 1556 to 1605. ",
            "keyString": "962301s29m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state was not the victim of \"The Subsidiary Alliance System\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mysore ",
            "optionB": "  Satara ",
            "optionC": "  Awadh ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatara state was not the victim of \"The Subsidiary Alliance System\". ",
            "keyString": "3868s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state was the first victim of \"The Subsidiary Alliance System\"?",
            "optionA": "  Satara ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Awadh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u2018The Nizam of Hyderabad\u2019 was the first victim of this policy. In AD 1798 it detached the Nizam from the French and also forbade having alliances with Maratha without British consent. ",
            "keyString": "3906s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Haldighati (1576) was a fight between Rajput and Mughal forces. Who led the Mughal forces?",
            "optionA": "  Man Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Jai Singh  ",
            "optionC": "  Khurram ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Haldighati was a battle fought on 18 June 1576 between cavalry and archers supporting the Rana of Mewar, Maharana Pratap; and the Mughal emperor Akbar's forces, led by Man Singh I of Amber. ",
            "keyString": "3925s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Pratihara ruler had the famous poet, Rajasekhara, at his court?",
            "optionA": "  Vatsaraja ",
            "optionB": "  Mahipala ",
            "optionC": "  Nagahhatta-II ",
            "optionD": "  Mihira Bhoja ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famous poet Rajasekhara lived in his court, and subsequently in the court of his son Mahipala. He was the author of Kavyamimansa, which contains a wealth of geographical data. Mahipala was the last important ruler of the Pratihara dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "3939s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Painting reached its highest level of development during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Paintings reached its Zenith during the reign of Mughal Emperor Jahangir. He patronised many great painters including Mansoou, Abul Hasan, Daswant and Basawan. ",
            "keyString": "3953s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The designation 'amil' during Akbar's reign denoted a",
            "optionA": "  Policeman ",
            "optionB": "  Retail trader ",
            "optionC": "  Postman ",
            "optionD": "  Revenue official ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe designation 'amil' during Akbar's reign denoted aRevenue official. ",
            "keyString": "43648s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar's son and successor Salim, on becoming the emperor, assumed the name of",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir Alampanah ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir Alamgir ",
            "optionD": "  Nuruddin Muhammad Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar's son and successor Salim, on becoming the emperor, assumed the name of Nuruddin Muhammad Jahangir. ",
            "keyString": "43684s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar defeated Durgawati and captured",
            "optionA": "  Bijapur ",
            "optionB": "  Jhansi ",
            "optionC": "  Gondwana ",
            "optionD": "  Surat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1562 CE, Akbar defeated Baz Bahadur and brought the region of Malwa under Mughal dominion. Simultaneously, Asaf Khan, a Mughal general, conquered Rewa, which lay north of Rani\u2019s kingdom. Thus, Garha-Mandla now touched the boundaries of both Rewa and Malwa, which were under the Mughals. An attack from either of them was imminent. ",
            "keyString": "43699s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Akbar of Kashmir who reconstructed and rehabilitated all the temples and asked Jonaraja to continue further Kalhana's Rajatarangini was",
            "optionA": "  Sikandar ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Mir Samsuddin ",
            "optionC": "  Zain-ul-Abidin ",
            "optionD": "  Saifuddin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Akbar of Kashmir who reconstructed and rehabilitated all the temples and asked Jonaraja to continue further Kalhana's Rajatarangini wasZain-ul-Abidin. ",
            "keyString": "43713s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hakim Mirza, the younger brother of Akbar was the viceroy of",
            "optionA": "  Kabul ",
            "optionB": "  Herat ",
            "optionC": "  Agra ",
            "optionD": "  Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShahzada Mirza Muhammad Hakim, sometimes known simply as Mirza Hakim, short: Mirza, was the second son of Mughal emperor Humayun. He ruled Kabul in Afghanistan, and often conflicted with his elder brother emperor Akbar. Mirza Hakim later on mended ways with Emperor Akbar. He is the son of Mah Chuchak Begum. He is known for writing Tajdar-e-Haram. ",
            "keyString": "43725s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The stone railing which Aurangzeb ordered to remove was presented to Keshav Rai Temple by",
            "optionA": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionB": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionC": "  Dara Shikoh ",
            "optionD": "  Dadaji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy order of Aurangzeb he had also forcibly removed, in 1666, the stone railing presented to the Keshav Rai temple by Dara Shikoh. ",
            "keyString": "80855s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full name of Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Muin-ud-din Mohammed Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Nuruddin Mohammed Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Jalal-ud-din Mohammed Aurangzeb ",
            "optionD": "  Nasiruddin Mohammed Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhi-ud-Din Muhammad also known as Aurangzeb or by his title Alamgir was the sixth emperor of the Mughal Empire. He ruled over most of the Indian subcontinent. His reign lasted for 49 years from 1658 until his death in 1707. ",
            "keyString": "80891s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following temples were destroyed by Aurangzeb?\nI. Somnath temple\nII. Vishwanath temple\nIII. Keshav Rai temple\nIV. Meenakshi temple",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTemples that were destroyed by Aurangzeb are Somnath temple, Vishwanath temple and Keshav Rai temple. ",
            "keyString": "80907s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is related to the Mughal emperor Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Replaced many Hindu temples with mosques ",
            "optionB": "  Promoted religious toleration ",
            "optionC": "  Converted to Hinduism ",
            "optionD": "  Presided over an era of religious harmony ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal emperor Aurangzeb replaced many Hindu temples with mosques. The original Kashi Vishwanath Temple was demolished by Aurangzeb, the sixth Mughal emperor who constructed the Gyanvapi Mosque atop the original Hindu temple. Kashi Vishwanath was among the most renowned Hindu temples of India. Even today the pillars and the structure of the original temple can be clearly seen. ",
            "keyString": "80926s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Sikh guru was executed by Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Tegh Bahadur ",
            "optionB": "  Arjun Dev ",
            "optionC": "  Hargobind ",
            "optionD": "  Gobind Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Guru was summoned to Delhi by Aurangzeb on a pretext, but when he arrived, he was offered, \"to abandon his faith, and convert to Islam\". Guru Tegh Bahadur refused, and he and his associates were arrested. He was executed on 11 November 1675 in public in Chandni Chowk, Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "80940s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun was born in the year",
            "optionA": "  1508 ",
            "optionB": "  1608 ",
            "optionC": "  1708 ",
            "optionD": "  1808 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHumayun was born on 17 March 1508, in Kabul, Mughal Empire (present-day Afghanistan), to Babur, the founder of the Mughal dynasty and his wife Maham Begum. ",
            "keyString": "119622s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun died in the year",
            "optionA": "  1536 ",
            "optionB": "  1546 ",
            "optionC": "  1556 ",
            "optionD": "  1566 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the evening of 21 Jan 1556, Humayun was walking in the terrace of his library at Sher Mandal in Delhi. While descending the steps, he heard the announcement for the evening prayer. He stood still upon the occasion and sat down on the second step till the proclamation was ended. When he was going to rise, he supported himself on a staff, which unfortunately slipped upon the marble, and he fell headlong from the top to the bottom of the stair. He was taken up insensible and laid upon his bed. He died on 24 Jan, at the age of fifty-one, after a reign of twenty-five years, in Kabul and India. ",
            "keyString": "119656s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun Nama was written by",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionD": "  Gulbadan Begum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe History of Humayun: Humayun Nama was written by Gul-badan Begam, Humayun' s sister. Gul-Badan Begum (1523 - 1603), was daughter of Zaheruddin Muhammad Babur of India. She wrote Humayun nama at the behest of her nephew and at the emperor of India Jalal-ud-din Muhammad Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "119670s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Humayun was in exile Koh-i-noor Diamond was with",
            "optionA": "  The Raja Bikramajid ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Tahmasp of Persia ",
            "optionC": "  Sultan of Bijapur ",
            "optionD": "  Sher Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Humayun was in exile Koh-i-noor Diamond was with Shah Tahmasp of Persia. ",
            "keyString": "119682s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who defeated Humayun in the battle of Chausa?",
            "optionA": "  Muhammad Adil Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Firoz Shah Suri ",
            "optionC": "  Sikandar Shah Suri ",
            "optionD": "  Sher Shah Suri ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Chausa (25 June 1539) took place between Mughal Emperor Humayun and Sher Shah Suri (Sher Khan). In this battle Humayun got defeated. ",
            "keyString": "119694s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Mughal period the registers of the agricultural lands were maintained by",
            "optionA": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionB": "  Qanungo ",
            "optionC": "  Amin ",
            "optionD": "  Krori ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Mughal period the registers of the agricultural lands were maintained by Qanungo. ",
            "keyString": "154157s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mir Bakshi of the Mughal Emperors was the head of",
            "optionA": "  Intelligence ",
            "optionB": "  Foreign affairs ",
            "optionC": "  Army organisation ",
            "optionD": "  Finance ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head of the military was called the mir bakshi, appointed from among the leading nobles of the court. The mir bakshi was in charge of intelligence gathering, and also made recommendations to the emperor for military appointments and promotions. ",
            "keyString": "154191s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Battle of Haldighati the Mughal troops were commanded by",
            "optionA": "  Asaf khan ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Man Singh of Amber ",
            "optionC": "  Qazi Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Todar Mal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Haldighati was a battle fought on 18 June 1576 between cavalry and archers supporting the Rana of Mewar, Maharana Pratap; and the Mughal emperor Akbar's forces, led by Man Singh I of Amber. ",
            "keyString": "154205s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Second battle of Panipat was fought between which two armies?",
            "optionA": "  Babur and Lodi Empire ",
            "optionB": "  Babur and Rana Sanga ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar and Hemu ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar and Rana of Mewar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecond Battle of Panipat was fought between Akbar & Hemu in 1556 in which Hemu was defeated. The original name of Hemu was Hemchand he was also known as 'Vikramaditya' & he was the 14th ruler who took the title of Vikramaditya.",
            "keyString": "154218s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Pala ruler founded the famous Vikramashila University for the Buddhists'?",
            "optionA": "  Mahipala ",
            "optionB": "  Devapala ",
            "optionC": "  Gopala ",
            "optionD": "  Dharmapala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVikramashila was founded by P\u0101la king Dharmapala in the late 8th or early 9th century. It prospered for about four centuries before it was destroyed by Bakhtiyar Khilji along with the other major centres of Buddhism in India around 1193. ",
            "keyString": "154229s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar was enthroned in a garden at",
            "optionA": "  Kalanaur ",
            "optionB": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionC": "  Gaur ",
            "optionD": "  Kabul ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe town has recorded essentialness as Mughal Emperor Akbar, was enthroned in a garden close to the Kalanaur by Bairam Khan. ",
            "keyString": "190539s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only Hindu Courtier of Akbar who accepted Din-i-Ilahi was",
            "optionA": "  Todermal ",
            "optionB": "  Birbal ",
            "optionC": "  Tansen ",
            "optionD": "  Man Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Birbal was the only Hindu to adopt Din-i-Ilahi, the religion founded by Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "190577s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ramayana was translated into Persian at Akbar's court by whom?",
            "optionA": "  Faizi ",
            "optionB": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionC": "  Badayuni ",
            "optionD": "  Haji Ibrahim Sirhindi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamayana was translated by Mulla Abdul Qadir Badayuni into Persian. ",
            "keyString": "190596s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the so-called 'Nine Gems of the Court of Akbar' the one who was a reputed poet of Hindi, was",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionB": "  Faizi ",
            "optionC": "  Abdur Rahim Khan-i-Khana ",
            "optionD": "  Birbal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhanzada Mirza Khan Abdul Rahim Khan-e-Khana (17 December 1556 \u2013 1627) also known as baba Rahim was a poet who lived during the rule of Mughal emperor Akbar. He was one of the nine important ministers (dewan) in his court, also known as the Navaratnas. ",
            "keyString": "190609s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the second capital of Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Fatehpur Sikri ",
            "optionD": "  Patna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Akbar's victory over Rajputanas of Chittor and Ranthambore, he shifted his capital from Agra to a new city which named 'Fatehpur Sikri' (the city of victory). ",
            "keyString": "190623s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The art of painting in the Mughal age was __________ in origin",
            "optionA": "  Persian ",
            "optionB": "  Hindu ",
            "optionC": "  French ",
            "optionD": "  Afghan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal painting is that particular style of South Asian painting which generally confines miniatures either as book illustrations or as single works to be kept in albums, which emerged from Persian miniature painting (itself largely of Chinese origin), with Indian Muslim, Hindu, Jain, and Buddhist influences, and developed largely in the court of the Mughal Empire of the 16th to 18th centuries. ",
            "keyString": "227310s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals one of the main imports was",
            "optionA": "  pepper ",
            "optionB": "  raw silk ",
            "optionC": "  cotton ",
            "optionD": "  opium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mughals one of the main imports wasraw silk. ",
            "keyString": "227346s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who built Imambara and Rumi Darwaza?",
            "optionA": "  Wajid Ali Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Asaf-ud-daula ",
            "optionC": "  Shuja-ud-daula ",
            "optionD": "  Adbdul Mansur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRumi Darwaza was built by the fourth Nawab of Lucknow, Nawab Asaf-ud-Daula and is believed to be identical to an old gate in Istanbul called Bab-i-H\u00fcmayun, and so is also sometimes referred to as Turkish Gate. The 60 feet high gate is now considered an architectural marvel, but it built for a noble purpose. ",
            "keyString": "227363s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following Mughal buildings is said to possess the unique feature of being exactly equal in length and breadth?",
            "optionA": "  Agra Fort ",
            "optionB": "  Red Fort ",
            "optionC": "  Taj Mahal ",
            "optionD": "  Buland Darwaza ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTaj Mahal was built by Mughal Emperor Shahjahan in memory of his beloved wife Mumtaz. It was designed by Ustad Ahmad Lahauri. The dome of Taj Mahal has exactly same height and the lenght of base i.e. 35 metres. ",
            "keyString": "227377s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Historian Abdul Hamid Lahori was in the court of",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbdul Hamid Lahori (died 1654) was a traveller and historian during the period of Shah Jahan who later became a court historian of Shah Jahan. ",
            "keyString": "227392s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had succeeded Mir Jumla as governor of Bengal in the reign of Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Siphr Sukoh ",
            "optionB": "  Izid Bakhsh ",
            "optionC": "  Shaista Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Shuja ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShaista Khan succeeded Mir Jumla as the governor of Bengal after his death. He gave personal attention to the problem of south Bengal, where the Magh (Arakanese) pirates, in conjunction with Portuguese pirates, had been terrorizing the area up to Dacca (capital of Bengal) from their headquarters at Chittagong. ",
            "keyString": "303993s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the reign of Aurangzeb, Rajaram was a",
            "optionA": "  Jat Leader ",
            "optionB": "  Mughal Leader ",
            "optionC": "  Maratha Leader ",
            "optionD": "  Sikh Leader ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajaram Raje Bhosale (24 February 1670 \u2013 3 March 1700 Sinhagad) was the younger son of Maratha ruler Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj, and half-brother of Sambhaji Maharaj. He took over the Maratha Empire as its third Chhatrapati after his brother's death at the hands of the Mughal emperor, Aurangzeb in 1689. ",
            "keyString": "304033s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On behalf of Aurangzeb Cooch Behar was seized by",
            "optionA": "  Mir Jumla ",
            "optionB": "  Prince Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Shayista Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Jai Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn behalf of Aurangzeb Cooch Behar was seized byMir Jumla. ",
            "keyString": "304050s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb put his father under house arrest in Agra Fort",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShah Jahan recovered from his illness, but Aurangzeb put his father under house arrest in Agra Fort from July 1658 until his death in January 1666. ",
            "keyString": "304065s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who did not revolt against Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Jats ",
            "optionB": "  Satnamis ",
            "optionC": "  Prince Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shayista Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShayista Khan did not revolt against Aurangzeb. ",
            "keyString": "304079s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not true about \"Doctrine of Lapse\"?",
            "optionA": "  It was started by Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  It was in operations between 1848 and 1856 ",
            "optionC": "  Nagpur was the first state annexed under this rule ",
            "optionD": "  Satara, jaipur, Jhansi and Nagpur states were annexed under this rule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatara was the first state annexed under this rule. ",
            "keyString": "349414s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Mansabdars\" in Mughal period were",
            "optionA": "  Landlords and zamindars ",
            "optionB": "  Officials of the state ",
            "optionC": "  Those who had to give revenue ",
            "optionD": "  Revenue collectors ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Mansabdars\" in Mughal period were Landlords and zamindars. ",
            "keyString": "349544s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Tipu Sultan?",
            "optionA": "  He was a Great admirer of Jagadguru Sankracharya of Sringeri ",
            "optionB": "  His autobiography was Tarikh-i-Khudai ",
            "optionC": "  He died during the fourth Anglo-Mysore war ",
            "optionD": "  He laid the foundation of Krishnaraj Sagar Dam on Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Fourth Anglo-Mysore War, the imperial forces of the British East India Company were supported by the Nizam of Hyderabad and Marathas. They defeated Tipu, and he was killed on 4 May 1799 while defending his fort of Srirangapatna. ",
            "keyString": "349592s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal period the main source of Imperial revenue was",
            "optionA": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  Customs duties ",
            "optionC": "  Industry ",
            "optionD": "  Foreign trade ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian agricultural production increased under the Mughal Empire. A variety of crops were grown, including food crops such as wheat, rice, and barley, and non-food cash crops such as cotton, indigo and opium. ",
            "keyString": "349631s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Jahangir promulgated twelve edicts for the general welfare and better government to mark his coronation\nII. Jahangir composed verses in Persian and sang Hindi lyrics\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJahangir promulgated twelve edicts for the general welfare and better government to mark his coronation. Jahangir composed verses in Persian and sang Hindi lyrics. ",
            "keyString": "349670s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The French East India Company was founded in",
            "optionA": "  1600 ",
            "optionB": "  1620 ",
            "optionC": "  1664 ",
            "optionD": "  1604 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJean-Baptiste Colbert founded the French East India Company in 1664. ",
            "keyString": "385844s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "__________was the first Mughal Emperor to acquire Koh-i-noor diamond",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar was the first Mughal Emperor to acquire Koh-i-noor diamond. ",
            "keyString": "385881s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The foreign traveller who visited Indian during the Mughal Period and who left us and expert description of the Peacock Throne, was",
            "optionA": "  Geronimo Verroneo ",
            "optionB": "  Omrah' Danishmand khan ",
            "optionC": "  Travernier ",
            "optionD": "  Austinof Bordeaux ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA foreign traveller who visited India during the Mughal period, was a jeweller and has left us an expert's description of the Peacock Throne, was Travernier. ",
            "keyString": "385899s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The treaty of Allahabad took place between __________",
            "optionA": "  Shuja-ud-daulah, Robert Clive and Shah Alam II ",
            "optionB": "  Shuja-ud-daulah, Mir jafar and Shah Alam II ",
            "optionC": "  Shuja-ud-daulah, Wajid Ali Shah and Shah Alam II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the Above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Treaty of Allahabad was signed on 12 August 1765, between the Mughal Emperor Shah Alam II, son of the late Emperor Alamgir II, and Robert Clive, of the East India Company, as a result of the Battle of Buxar of 22 October 1764. ",
            "keyString": "385915s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal period there was continuous emigration of the __________ to places ruled by Hindu Rajas",
            "optionA": "  Nobles ",
            "optionB": "  Poor ",
            "optionC": "  Middle Class ",
            "optionD": "  Foreign residents ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the Mughal period there was continuous emigration of the poor to places ruled by Hindu Rajas. ",
            "keyString": "385930s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jahangir (1605-1627 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Haryanka ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Mughal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMirza Nur-ud-din Beig Muhammad Khan Salim, known by his imperial name Jahangir (31 August 1569 \u2013 28 October 1627), was the fourth Mughal Emperor who ruled from 1605 until his death in 1627. ",
            "keyString": "452039s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) is/are correct related to Mughal Emperor Jahangir?\nI. Jahangir claimed that he could distinguish the work of different artists in a single picture.\nII. Painting was at its climax during his reign.",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJahangir claimed that he could distinguish the work of different artists in a single picture. Painting was at its climax during his reign. ",
            "keyString": "452070s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the undermentioned facts about Taj Mahal is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  It is a magnificent  Mausoleum ",
            "optionB": "  It was built by Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  It is situated outside Agra Fort ",
            "optionD": "  The names of artisans who builtd it are engraved on it ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe names of artisans who build it are not engraved on it. ",
            "keyString": "452087s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ibadat Khana was a meeting house built by which Mughal Emperor?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ibadat Khana (House of Worship) was a meeting house built in 1575 CE by the Mughal Emperor Akbar (r. 1556\u20131605) at Fatehpur Sikri to gather spiritual leaders of different religious grounds so as to conduct a discussion on the teachings of the respective religious leaders. ",
            "keyString": "452099s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first invasion of India by Sultan Mahmud Ghazni was in",
            "optionA": "  1004 AD ",
            "optionB": "  1001 AD ",
            "optionC": "  1000 AD ",
            "optionD": "  999 AD ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahmud of Ghazni first invaded modern Afghanistan and Pakistan in 1000 AD. He defeated Hindu shahi kingdom ruler Jaya Pala, who killed himself later, and his son Ananda Pala became his successor. 1006 : Ghazni invaded Multan. ",
            "keyString": "452111s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1542 Akbar was born at",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Herat ",
            "optionC": "  Umarkot ",
            "optionD": "  Kabul ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar (Abu'l-Fath Jalal ud-din Muhammad Akbar, 15 October 1542 \u2013 1605) was the 3rd Mughal Emperor. He was born in Umerkot,(now Pakistan). He was the son of 2nd Mughal Emperor Humayun. Akbar became the king in 1556 at the age of 13 when his father died. ",
            "keyString": "563491s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was built by Akbar to commemorate his conquest of Khandesh in Gujarat?",
            "optionA": "  Bada Imambara ",
            "optionB": "  Buland Darwaza ",
            "optionC": "  Jama Masjid ",
            "optionD": "  Siddi Bashir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuland Darwaza (The Gate of Magnificience) was built by Mughal Emperor Akbar in 1601 at Fatehpur Sikri (U.P.). It was built by Akbar to commemorate his victory over Khandesh in Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "564146s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the regent of Akbar in his early days?",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionB": "  Bairam Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Tansen ",
            "optionD": "  Todarmal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBairam Khan also Bayram Khan ( c. 18 January 1501 \u2013 c. 31 January 1561) was an important military commander, later commander-in-chief of the Mughal army, a powerful statesman and regent at the court of the Mughal Emperors, Humayun and Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "564726s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the age of Akbar at the time of his coronation at Kalanaur?",
            "optionA": "  Thirteen ",
            "optionB": "  Fifteen ",
            "optionC": "  Eighteen ",
            "optionD": "  Twenty ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Emperor Akbar aseended the throne at the age of thirteen in the year 1556 A.D. ",
            "keyString": "565271s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two women who, while conducting the affairs of their states faced Akbar's wars of conquest were Rani Durgawati and Chand Bibi (or Sultana), respectively of",
            "optionA": "  Jaisalmer and Khandesh ",
            "optionB": "  Malwa and Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Gondwana and Ahmadnagar ",
            "optionD": "  Ranathambhor and Khandesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo women who, while conducting the affairs of their states faced Akbar's wars of conquest were Rani Durgawati and Chand Bibi (or Sultana), respectively of Gondwana and Ahmadnagar. ",
            "keyString": "565792s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Mughal monarchs has vividly described Indian flora & fauna, seasons, fruits etc. in his diary?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Babur ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Mughal Emperor Babur and Emperor Jahangir have visibly described Indian flora, fauna and season & fruit in his diary. But option 'C' is more accurate. ",
            "keyString": "670025s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals the Governor was popularly known as",
            "optionA": "  Subahdar ",
            "optionB": "  Wazir ",
            "optionC": "  Vakil ",
            "optionD": "  Faujdar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principal officer was the governor, called sipah salar under Akbar and nazim under his successors, but popularly known as subahdar and later only as subah. ",
            "keyString": "676184s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the last Mughal emperor?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Noor Jehan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbu Zafar Sirajuddin Muhammad Bahadur Shah Zafar, also known as Bahadur Shah or Bahadur Shah II (October 1775 - 7 November 1862) was the last of the Mughal emperors in India, as well as the last ruler of the Timurid Dynasty. He was the son of Akbar Shah II and Lalbai, who was a Hindu Rajput. ",
            "keyString": "677415s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following rulers abolished Jiziya?",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Balban ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJizya was abolished by the third Mughal emperor Akbar, in 1564. It was finally abolished in 1579. ",
            "keyString": "678113s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct order (first to last) of states annexed under the policy of \"Doctrine of Lapse\"?",
            "optionA": "  Satara > Jaipur > Sambhalpur> Bahat ",
            "optionB": "  Jaipur > Satara > Sambhalpur> Bahat ",
            "optionC": "  Bahat >Satara > Jaipur > Sambhalpur ",
            "optionD": "  Satara > Jaipur > Bahat> Sambhalpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe company took over the princely states of Satara (1848), Jaitpur and Sambalpur (1849), Nagpur and Jhansi (1854), Tore and Arcot (1855) and Udaipur (Chhattisgarh) under the terms of the doctrine of lapse. Oudh (1856) is widely believed to have under the Doctrine of Lapse. ",
            "keyString": "679010s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Bara Imambara located?",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionC": "  Patna ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBara Imambara, also known as Asafi Imambara is an imambara complex in Lucknow, India built by Asaf-ud-Daula, Nawab of Awadh in 1784. Bara means big. ",
            "keyString": "790552s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals the jizya was collected from",
            "optionA": "  Persians ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammadans ",
            "optionC": "  Hindus ",
            "optionD": "  Foreign visitors ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJizya tax was protection money. Muslims have been charging it not only from hindus in the past but from any non-muslim citizens in a territory they rule. ",
            "keyString": "790633s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Mughal emperor of India was",
            "optionA": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Babur ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal Empire was founded by Babur (reigned 1526\u20131530), a Central Asian ruler who was descended from the Turco-Mongol conqueror Timur (the founder of the Timurid Empire) on his father's side and from Chagatai, the second son of the Mongol ruler Genghis Khan, on his mother's side. ",
            "keyString": "790662s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The peacock throne was constructed by the Mughal Emperor",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Peacock Throne was a jewelled throne built by Emperor Shah Jahan in the early 17th century. It was kept in the Diwan- e- Khas of the Red Fort in Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "790682s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The writer of Ram Charit Manas, Tulsidas, was related to which ruler?",
            "optionA": "  Chandragupta Maurya ",
            "optionB": "  Nawab Vajib Ali Sah ",
            "optionC": "  Harsha ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRam Charit Manas is considered by national and International scholars as one of the greatest pieces of literature ever written in the world. Tulsidas was a contemporary of Mughal emperor Akbar. But Hindutva forces have generally pitted Tulsidas against Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "790698s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal queen, whose name was inscribed on the coins and on all royal farmans as well as attached to the imperial signature was",
            "optionA": "  Jodha Bai ",
            "optionB": "  Nur Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Mumtaz Mahal ",
            "optionD": "  Ladli Begum ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal queen, whose name was inscribed on the coins and on all royal farmans as well as attached to the imperial signature was Nur Jahan. ",
            "keyString": "846544s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal troops were largely drawn from",
            "optionA": "  The Rajput Chiefs ",
            "optionB": "  Tributary Chiefs ",
            "optionC": "  Mansabdars ",
            "optionD": "  Central Contingents ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mansabdar was a military unit within the administrative system of the Mughal Empire introduced by Akbar. The word mansab is of Arabic origin meaning rank or position. The system, hence, determined the rank of a government official and also other military generals. Every civil and military officer was given a 'mansab' and different which could be increased by ten were used for ranking officers. ",
            "keyString": "846659s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal painting reached its zenith during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar-II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal paintings reached its zenith during the reign of Emperor Jahangir. He patronized many great painters like Mansoon, Abul Hasan, Daswant and Basawan. ",
            "keyString": "846731s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mughal painting reached its zenith during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Both (A) and (B) above ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal paintings reached its zenith during the reign of Emperor Jahangir. He patronized many great painters like Mansoon, Abul Hasan, Daswant and Basawan. ",
            "keyString": "846785s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Mughal emperors, brought about the fall of Sayyid Brothers?",
            "optionA": "  Bahadur Shah-I ",
            "optionB": "  Rafi-ud-daulah ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Jahan-II ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammad Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSayyid Brothers Abdulla Khan (Wazir) and Hussain Ali Khan (Mir Bakshi) were the generals in Mughal army. They became very influential after the death of Emperor Aurangzeb. When Mughal Emperor Muhammad Shah ascended the throne, he took even the full control and got the killed. They also known as \"King Makers\". ",
            "keyString": "846842s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Aurangzeb proceeded against Golconda it was ruled by",
            "optionA": "  Sikandar ",
            "optionB": "  Durga Devi ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Hasan ",
            "optionD": "  Afzal Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Siege of Golconda occurred in January 1687, when Mughal Emperor Aurangzeb led his forces to besiege the Qutb Shahi dynasty at Golconda Fort (also known as the Diamond Capital of its time) and was home to the Kollur Mine. The ruler of Golconda was the well entrenched Abul Hasan Qutb Shah. ",
            "keyString": "904490s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assuming the title of Alamgir, Aurangzeb crowned himself as Emperor on July 21, 1658 at",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangabad ",
            "optionC": "  Fatehpur Sikri ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Shah Jahan fell ill in September 1657, Aurangzeb challenged Dara, defeated him, imprisoned their father, and assumed imperial authority on July 21, 1658. After liquidating his three brothers, he crowned himself emperor of India, assuming the title Alamgir (Conqueror of the World) at Delhi on June 5, 1659. ",
            "keyString": "905146s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb (1658-1707 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Mughal ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Haryanka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe last of the great Mughals was Aurangzeb (r. 1658-1707), who seized the throne by killing all his brothers and imprisoning his own father. Aurangzeb was the third son of the Mughal emperor Shah Jahan; his mother was Mumtaz Mahal, who is buried in the Taj Mahal. ",
            "keyString": "905418s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb died in the year",
            "optionA": "  1760 ",
            "optionB": "  1764 ",
            "optionC": "  1707 ",
            "optionD": "  1700 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb died in the year 3 March 1707 (aged 88) Ahmednagar, India. ",
            "keyString": "905776s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb was the son of",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb was born on 3 November 1618, in Dahod, Gujarat. He was the third son and sixth child of Shah Jahan and Mumtaz Mahal. ",
            "keyString": "906136s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar had incorporated some principles of social reforms in the Din-i-illahi. Which of the following social reforms did not form part of Din-i- illahi?",
            "optionA": "  Remarriage of widows ",
            "optionB": "  Prohibition of child marriage ",
            "optionC": "  Monogamy ",
            "optionD": "  Rejection of seclusion of women ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRejection of seclusion of women social reforms did not form part of din-i- ilahi. ",
            "keyString": "949665s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not related to the Akbar's reign?",
            "optionA": "  Religious toleration for Hindus and Sikhs ",
            "optionB": "  A syncretic religion, called \"divine faith,\" which stressed loyalty to the emperor ",
            "optionC": "  A centralized administrative structure with ministers appointed to regional provinces ",
            "optionD": "  Education and basic rights for Indian women ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEducation and basic rights for Indian women is not related to the Akbar's reign. ",
            "keyString": "949849s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To bring Hindu-Muslim unity, Akbar",
            "optionA": "  encouraged cow-killing ",
            "optionB": "  prohibited cow-killing ",
            "optionC": "  taxed cow-killing ",
            "optionD": "  remained silent to cow-killing ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo bring Hindu-Muslim unity, Akbar prohibited cow-killing. He banned killing of animals. He stopped eating meat for many months. ",
            "keyString": "949953s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who were 'Jagirdars' during the reign of Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Large estate owners ",
            "optionB": "  Officials of state who were given jagir in place of cash pay ",
            "optionC": "  Revenue collectors ",
            "optionD": "  Autonomous rulers under Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis feudal system of land ownership is referred to as the jagirdar system. The system was introduced by the Sultans of Delhi from the 13th century onwards, was later adopted by the Mughal Empire, and continued under the British East India Company. ",
            "keyString": "950048s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only Hindu noble at the court of Akbar to accept the Din-i-llahi was",
            "optionA": "  Man Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Todar Mal ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagwan Das ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Birbal was the only Hindu to adopt Din-i-Ilahi, the religion founded by Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "950139s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the war of succession who had supported Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Jahanara ",
            "optionB": "  Zebunisha ",
            "optionC": "  Jintunisha ",
            "optionD": "  Roshanara ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRoshanara's rise to power began when she successfully foiled a plot by her father and Dara Shikoh to kill Aurangzeb. According to history, Shah Jahan sent a letter of invitation to Aurangzeb to visit Delhi, in order to peacefully resolve the family crisis. In truth, however, Shah Jahan planned to capture, imprison and kill Aurangazeb in prison as he viewed his third son as a serious threat to the throne. When Roshanara got wind of her father's plots, she sent a messenger to Aurangzeb, outlining their father's true intentions, and warning Aurangazeb to stay away from Delhi. Aurangzeb was extremely grateful to Roshanara for her timely warning. When the war of succession was resolved in favour of Aurangzeb, she quickly became a powerful figure at court. ",
            "keyString": "991513s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Aurangzeb's reign, which of the following were not included in his government?",
            "optionA": "  Rajputs ",
            "optionB": "  Marathas ",
            "optionC": "  Pathans ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring his reign, the Mughal Empire extended from the Himalayas to Karnataka and Gujarat to Bengal. However he faced lot of rebels from the Jat, Maratha as well as Sikh community. Marathas were not included in Aurangzeb's government. ",
            "keyString": "991549s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Aurangzeb abolished Rahdari, Pandari and Pilgrim tax.\nII. Aurangzeb discontinued the practice of inscribing the Kalima on the coins.\nWhich of the above statements is/are correct related to Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only II ",
            "optionC": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFormerly Kalima used to be embossed on the coins. This practice was abandoned by Aurangzeb as it was un-Islamic. ",
            "keyString": "991566s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most decisive battle between the forces of Dara and Aurangzeb (in the war of Succession) was fought at",
            "optionA": "  Dharmat ",
            "optionB": "  Samugarh ",
            "optionC": "  Deorai ",
            "optionD": "  Khajwa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBattle of Samugarh, Jang-e-Samugarh, (May 29, 1658), was a decisive battle in the struggle for the throne during the Mughal war of succession (1658\u20131659) between the sons of the Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan after the emperor's serious illness in September 1657. ",
            "keyString": "991584s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bibi Ka Maqbara was erected by __________ at Aurangabad and is a replica of the Taj Mahal",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Bahadur Shah Zafar ",
            "optionC": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bibi Ka Maqbara (English:\"Tomb of the Lady\") is a tomb located in Aurangabad, Maharashtra, India. It was built by Mughal emperor Aurangzeb's son Azam Shah in the memory of his mother (posthumously known as Rabia-ud-Daurani). ",
            "keyString": "991597s30m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal ruler's reign has been described as the golden age of medieval art and architecture?",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir's ",
            "optionB": "  Babur's ",
            "optionC": "  Humayun's ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Jahan's ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe age of Shah Jahan(January 1628-July 1658) is considered to be the golden age in Mughal Empire because during his reign there was peace in the country.There were no foreign threats. He did a lot of work for the welfare of people like he constructed roads, canals, sarais etc. ",
            "keyString": "31224s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following traders first came to India during the Mughal period?",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Dutch ",
            "optionC": "  Danish ",
            "optionD": "  Britis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPortuguese traders first came to India during the Mughal period. ",
            "keyString": "31308s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Mughal Emperor became the first pensioner of the East India Company?",
            "optionA": "  Ahmed Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar II ",
            "optionC": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammed Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar II (22 April 1760 \u2013 28 September 1837), also known as Akbar Shah II, was the penultimate Mughal emperor of India. He reigned from 1806 to 1837. ",
            "keyString": "31330s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Mughal General who conquered Assam, Chittagong, etc. in the north-east was",
            "optionA": "  Shaista Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Jumla ",
            "optionC": "  Mirza Raja Jai Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Jaswant Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe famous Mughal General who conquered Assam, Chittagong, etc. in the north-east was Mir Jumla. ",
            "keyString": "31348s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal government can be described as an/a",
            "optionA": "  Autocracy ",
            "optionB": "  Liberal monarchy ",
            "optionC": "  Centralised despotism ",
            "optionD": "  Absolute monarchy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mughal government was a centralized despotism. In such a system everything depended upon the personality and character of the monarch. ",
            "keyString": "31364s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Akbar's regime,__________  was the military head",
            "optionA": "  Sultan Ahmed Fawad ",
            "optionB": "  Suri Moja ",
            "optionC": "  Mir Khaas ",
            "optionD": "  Mir Bakshi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head of the military was called the mir bakshi, appointed from among the leading nobles of the court. The mir bakshi was in charge of intelligence gathering, and also made recommendations to the emperor for military appointments and promotions. ",
            "keyString": "74071s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fortress of Asirgarh was under the rule of __________ when Akbar besieged it",
            "optionA": "  Mansingh ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Bhagvan Das ",
            "optionC": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Hemu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar occupied Burhanpur and besieged Asirgarh Fort in 1599, and took it on 17 January 1601, when Miran Bahadur Shah refused to submit Khandesh. ",
            "keyString": "74108s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote Akbarnama?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Birbal ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Fazal ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagavan Das ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbdul Fazal was one of the navratnas at Akbar's court. He wrote 'Akbamama' which is the official history of Akbar's reign. ",
            "keyString": "74126s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the name of the Hall of Worship constructed by Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Diwan-e-khas ",
            "optionB": "  Diwan-e-Aam ",
            "optionC": "  Ibadat Khana ",
            "optionD": "  Buland Darwaza ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ibadat Khana (House of Worship) was a meeting house built in 1575 CE by the Mughal Emperor Akbar (r. 1556\u20131605) at Fatehpur Sikri to gather spiritual leaders of different religious grounds so as to conduct a discussion on the teachings of the respective religious leaders. ",
            "keyString": "74140s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was appointed by Akbar as his Court Musician?",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazal ",
            "optionB": "  Miyan Tansen ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Birbal ",
            "optionD": "  Raja Todar Mal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar considered Miyan Tansen as a Navaratnas (nine jewels), and gave him the title Mian, an honorific, meaning learned man. Tansen was a composer, musician and vocalist, to whom a large number of compositions have been attributed in northern regions of the Indian subcontinent. ",
            "keyString": "74153s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced Mansabdari system in India?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mansabdari system was the administrative system introduced by Akbar in Mughal Empire during 1571. The word 'Mansab' is of Arabic origin meaning rank or position. Hence, Mansabdari was a system of ranking the government officials and determined their civil & military duties, along with their renumerations. ",
            "keyString": "115197s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazal  Chief  -Advisor ",
            "optionB": "  Faizi - Poet ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal - Finance Minister ",
            "optionD": "  All are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBirbal was one of the nine Jews in the court of Akbar, he was not the finance minister. Todarmal was the finance minister of Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "115230s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was an illiterate?",
            "optionA": "  Jahagir ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar remained illiterate and uneducated all his life. He had to occupy the throne at the early age of 13 years after the untimely death of his father Humayun. The responsibilities of the Great Mughal Empire never allowed him the time to educate himself. ",
            "keyString": "115244s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the cause of disintegration of the Mughal Empire?",
            "optionA": "  War of succession among sons of Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Attacks of Nadir Shah and Ahmad Shah Abdali ",
            "optionC": "  Revolts of various communities like Jats, Sikhs, Rajputs etc. ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above mentioned factors contributed to the downfall of the Mughal Empire. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWar of succession among sons of Aurangzeb. 9Attacks of Nadir Shah and Ahmad Shah Abdali. Revolts of various communities like Jats, Sikhs, Rajputs etc. All of the above mentioned factors contributed to the downfall of the Mughal Empire. ",
            "keyString": "115257s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The well-known painting showing the arrival at the Mughal Court of the great singer Tansen exhibits",
            "optionA": "  The Persian Style ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhara Style ",
            "optionC": "  Hindu Style ",
            "optionD": "  The fusion of the Mughal and Hindu Styles ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe well-known painting of the arrival of Tansen, the legendary singer at the court of Akbar, shows the fusion of this Persian and Hindu styles of art. ",
            "keyString": "115269s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The battle between Babur and Rana Sanga was fought at",
            "optionA": "  Panipat ",
            "optionB": "  Chunar ",
            "optionC": "  Khanwa ",
            "optionD": "  Jaunpur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Khanwa was fought near the village of Khanwa, in Bharatpur District of Rajasthan, on March 16, 1527. It was fought between the invading forces of the first Mughal Emperor Babur and the Rajput forces led by Rana Sanga of Mewar, after the Battle of Panipat. ",
            "keyString": "154930s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Babur won the first Battle of Panipat.\nReason (R): Babur was the first to introduce the use of cannons in India.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1526, the First Battle of Panipat saw the introduction of massed artillery tactics to Indian warfare. Under the guidance of Ottoman gun master Ustad Ali Quli, Babur deployed cannons behind a screening row of carts. ",
            "keyString": "154963s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur's autobiography, called Tuzuk-i-Baburi or Baburnama, which is reckoned among \"the most enthralling and romantic works in the literature of all times\" is written in",
            "optionA": "  Arabic ",
            "optionB": "  Persian ",
            "optionC": "  Turki ",
            "optionD": "  Urdu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabar's autobiography, called Tuzuk-i-Baburi or Baburnama, which is reckoned among \u201cthe most enthralling and romantic works in the literature of all times\" is written in Turki. ",
            "keyString": "154978s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Babur was originally the ruler of",
            "optionA": "  Kabul ",
            "optionB": "  Persia ",
            "optionC": "  Fargana ",
            "optionD": "  Khandahar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur was born in Andijan, in the Fergana Valley, in modern Uzbekistan. He was the eldest son of Umar Sheikh Mirza, governor of Fergana and great grandson of Timur the Great. ",
            "keyString": "154991s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Babur died?",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Kabul ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur died in 1530 in Agra and was succeeded by Humayun. He was first buried in Agra but, as per his wishes, his mortal remains were moved to Kabul reburied. ",
            "keyString": "155002s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals, the Police duties in urban areas were entrusted to the officers known as",
            "optionA": "  Kotwal ",
            "optionB": "  Kazi ",
            "optionC": "  Vakil ",
            "optionD": "  Amin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mughals, all police duties in the cities and towns were entrusted to the 'Kotwal'. He was essentially an urban officer, being chief on the city police. ",
            "keyString": "195509s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Mughal ruler who tried to create affinity between Sikh and Maratha by granted the right to collect Sardesh Mukhi of Deccan but not Chauth to the Marathas?",
            "optionA": "  Jahander Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Muazzam ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Farukhsiyar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuazzam tried to create affinity between Sikh and Maratha. He granted the right to collect Sardesh Mukhi of Deccan but not Chauth to the Marathas. ",
            "keyString": "195542s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Battle of Buxar fought between __________",
            "optionA": "  The English, the Nawab of Bengal and the French ",
            "optionB": "  Mir Kasim, the Nawab of Bengal, Nawab of Oudh and Shah Alam II, The Mughal Emperor ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar II, the Nawab of Bengal and Nawab of Oudh ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar II, the Nawab of Bengal and the Marathas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Buxar was fought in 1764, between the British and the armies of Mir Qasim, Mughal Emperor Shah Alam-II and Shuja-ud-Daulah , Nawab of Awadh in Buxar(in Bihar). The battle was won by forces of British East India company. The British won this battle under the command of Hector Munro. ",
            "keyString": "195556s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "First Anglo Sikh War fought between __________",
            "optionA": "  The English & French ",
            "optionB": "  The English & Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  The English & king Dalip Singh ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Anglo-Sikh War was fought between the Sikh Empire and the East India Company between 1845 and 1846. It resulted in partial subjugation of the Sikh kingdom and cession of Jammu and Kashmir as a separate princely state under British suzerainty. ",
            "keyString": "195569s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was also known as 'Zinda Pir'?",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb was called \u201cZinda Pir\u201dor \u201cLiving Saint \u201d in Mughal India. He banned on Nauroj festival, Tuladan, Jharokha etc, he restarted Jizya Tax. ",
            "keyString": "195581s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following forts was not built by Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Gwalior Fort ",
            "optionB": "  Agra Fort ",
            "optionC": "  Lahore Fort ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad Fort ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGwalior Fort was built by Raja Man Sing Tomar in 8th century. It consists of one defensive structure and two main palaces ( Gujrat Mahal and Man Mandir ). ",
            "keyString": "233594s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A renowned Jain scholar who was greatly honoured by Akbar was",
            "optionA": "  Hemachandra ",
            "optionB": "  Harivijaya ",
            "optionC": "  Vastupala ",
            "optionD": "  Bhadrabahu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar invited Bhattarak Harvijay Suri the main exponent of Jain Swetambara sect. ",
            "keyString": "233626s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was the biographer of Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionB": "  Faizi ",
            "optionC": "  Abdul Nabi Khan ",
            "optionD": "  Birbal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAin-i-Akbari (The constitution of Akbar) is the third volume of 'Akbarnama' (the book of Akbar) was written by Abul Fazal. He was the court poet of Mughal Emperor Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "233639s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Rajput dynasty had not surrendered to Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Pratihara ",
            "optionB": "  Sisodiya ",
            "optionC": "  Rathor ",
            "optionD": "  Parmar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSisodiya dynasty that ruled mewar did not surrender to emperor Akbar until and unless Jahangir defeated Rana Pratap's Son. ",
            "keyString": "233651s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest historian of the reign of Akbar, who wrote Akbarnama and Ain-i-Akbari, was",
            "optionA": "  Nizamuddin Ahmad ",
            "optionB": "  Abdur Qadir Badauni ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionD": "  Abdas Khan Arwani ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Akbarnama which translates to Book of Akbar, is the official chronicle of the reign of Akbar, the third Mughal Emperor (r. 1556\u20131605), commissioned by Akbar himself by his court historian and biographer, Abu'l-Fazl ibn Mubarak who was one of the nine jewels in Akbar's court. He had also written Ain-i-Akbari. ",
            "keyString": "233662s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Birbal was an advisor in the court of?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionD": "  Jahangir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBirbal is a famous historical character and he was a court jester in the court of Mughal Emperor Jalaluddin Mohammed Akbar. He was one among the nine jewels or 'Nav Ratnas' in the court of Akbar. He was in the inner council of advisors of Akbar's administration. ",
            "keyString": "276277s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal emperor was a great musician, a great patron of Hindustani Music and was popularly known as Rangila?",
            "optionA": "  Bahdur Shah I ",
            "optionB": "  Bahadur Shah II ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmad Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad Shah was a great patron of the arts, including musical, cultural and administrative developments. His pen-name was Sada Rangila (\"ever joyous\") and he is often referred to as \"Muhammad Shah Rangila\", also sometimes as \"Bahadur Shah Rangila\" after his grand father Bahadur Shah I. ",
            "keyString": "276353s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the battle of Buxar fought?",
            "optionA": "  October 1764 ",
            "optionB": "  October 1754 ",
            "optionC": "  Sept. 1564 ",
            "optionD": "  Jan. 1824 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Battle of Buxar was fought on 22 October 1764 between the forces under the command of the British East India Company, led by Hector Munro, and the combined armies of Mir Qasim, Nawab of Bengal till 1763; the Nawab of Awadh; and the Mughal Emperor Shah Alam II. ",
            "keyString": "276373s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which European power was the last who reached India?",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  Germans ",
            "optionC": "  The French ",
            "optionD": "  The Dutch ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrance was the last of the major European maritime powers of the 17th century to enter the East India trade. ",
            "keyString": "276392s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Din-i-Ilahi\" was the new religion started by",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Shahjahan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Din-i Ilahi (lit. \"Religion of God\") was a syncretic religion propounded by the Mughal emperor Akbar in 1582 CE, intending to merge some of the elements of the religions of his empire, and thereby reconcile the differences that divided his subjects. ",
            "keyString": "276410s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar held his religious discussion in",
            "optionA": "  Jodhabai's Palace ",
            "optionB": "  Panch Mahal ",
            "optionC": "  Ibadat Khana ",
            "optionD": "  Buland Darwaza ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ibadat Khana (House of Worship) was a meeting house built in 1575 CE by the Mughal Emperor Akbar (r. 1556\u20131605) at Fatehpur Sikri to gather spiritual leaders of different religious grounds so as to conduct a discussion on the teachings of the respective religious leaders. ",
            "keyString": "317590s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the master of imperial mint at Delhi during the reign of Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Khwaza Abdus Samad ",
            "optionB": "  Mansur ",
            "optionC": "  Mir Sayyid Ali ",
            "optionD": "  Jehangir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhwaza Abdus Samad was the master of imperial mint at Delhi during the reign of Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "317628s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The architectural raw material generally used in Akbar's period was",
            "optionA": "  Marble ",
            "optionB": "  Brick ",
            "optionC": "  Limestone ",
            "optionD": "  Redstone ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe architectural raw material generally used in Akbar's period was Redstone. ",
            "keyString": "317646s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the trusted General of the Mughal emperor Akbar?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Todar Mal ",
            "optionB": "  Man Singh I ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal ",
            "optionD": "  Tansen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Man Singh was the most trusted General of the Mughal emperor Akbar, he assisted him in many battles including the famous Battle of Haldighati (1576). ",
            "keyString": "317659s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Akbar's reign who was the Finance Minister of the Mughal empire?",
            "optionA": "  Raja Todar Mal ",
            "optionB": "  Man Singh-I ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal ",
            "optionD": "  Tansen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaja Todarmal was the finance minister (Mushrif-i-Diwan) of Mughal Emperor Akbar, he was one of the navratnas of Akbar's court. He introduced land measurement system, Zabti/Dhasala system (revenue collection) and karori system. ",
            "keyString": "317672s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb, in his attempt to annex Marwar to the Mughal empire, was involved in a 30-year war. During these long years the most valiant struggle from the side of Marwar was fought by",
            "optionA": "  Ajit Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Durgadas ",
            "optionC": "  Hadas of Bundi ",
            "optionD": "  Indra Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb, in his attempt to annex Marwar to the Mughal empire, was involved in a 30-year war. During these long years the most valiant struggle from the side of Marwar was fought byDurgadas Rathore. ",
            "keyString": "352350s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Musamman Burj is situated inside the Fatehpur Sikri Fort\nII. Aurangzeb built Moti Masjid inside Agra Fort\nWhich of the following option is correct related to the Mughal Architecture?",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II are incorrect ",
            "optionC": "  Only I is correct ",
            "optionD": "  Only II is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMusamman Burj also known as the Saman Burj or the Shah-burj, is an octagonal tower standing close to the Shah Jahan's private hall Diwan-e-Khas in Agra Fort. The Moti Masjid (translation: Pearl Mosque) in Agra was built by Shah Jahan. ",
            "keyString": "352383s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb appointed his uncle Shaista Khan as Governor of",
            "optionA": "  Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Deccan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1660 Aurangzeb appointed Shaista Khan, his maternal uncle and a veteran general, viceroy of the Deccan, with instructions to suppress the activities of Shivaji. ",
            "keyString": "352400s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these is not one of the titles adopted by Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Alamgir ",
            "optionB": "  Padshah ",
            "optionC": "  Sultan Sulaiman ",
            "optionD": "  Ghazi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSuleiman I, commonly known as Suleiman the Magnificent in the West and Kanuni Sultan Suleyman in his realm, was the tenth and longest-reigning Sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1520 until his death in 1566. ",
            "keyString": "352412s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who amongst the following succeeded Aurangzeb?",
            "optionA": "  Azam shah ",
            "optionB": "  Kam Baksh ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar-II ",
            "optionD": "  Mauzzam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbu'l Faaiz Qutb-ud-Din Muhammad Azam (28 June 1653 \u2013 8 June 1707), commonly known as Azam Shah (\"King Azam\"), was a titular Mughal emperor, who reigned from 14 March 1707 to 8 June 1707. He was the eldest son of the sixth Mughal emperor Aurangzeb (also known as Alamgir) and his chief consort Dilras Banu Begum. ",
            "keyString": "352424s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bahadur Shah (First) was born in the year",
            "optionA": "  1543 ",
            "optionB": "  1643 ",
            "optionC": "  1743 ",
            "optionD": "  1843 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBahadur Shah-I was the seventh Mughal Emperor. He was the third son of the Mughal Emperor Aurangzeb and Nawab Bai. He was born on Oct 14,1643. ",
            "keyString": "434105s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shah Jahan built the Moti Masjid at",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionC": "  Agra ",
            "optionD": "  Amarkot ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Moti Masjid in Agra was built by Shah Jahan. During the rule of Shah Jahan the Mughal emperor, numerous architectural wonders were built, the most famous of them being the Taj Mahal. Moti Masjid earned the epithet Pearl Mosque for it shone like a pearl. ",
            "keyString": "434141s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shah Jahan was kept in prison by Aurangzeb at",
            "optionA": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Daulatabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShah Jahan recovered from his illness, but Aurangzeb put his father under house arrest in Agra Fort from July 1658 until his death in January 1666. ",
            "keyString": "434157s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal ruler, Bahadur Shah II had been exiled by the British and sent to",
            "optionA": "  Andman and Nicobar ",
            "optionB": "  Fatehpur Sikri ",
            "optionC": "  Mandalay ",
            "optionD": "  Rangoon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBahadur Shah II's involvement in the Indian Rebellion of 1857, the British exiled him to Rangoon in British-controlled Burma (now in Myanmar), after convicting him on conspiracy charges. ",
            "keyString": "434171s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who called Muazzam as Shahi-i- Bekhabar?",
            "optionA": "  Kafi Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Zulfikar khan ",
            "optionC": "  Kam Baksh ",
            "optionD": "  Nur Jahan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKafi Khan called Muazzam as Shahi-i- Bekhabar. ",
            "keyString": "434183s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aurangzeb sent Mukarrab Khan against",
            "optionA": "  Shaji Bhonsle ",
            "optionB": "  Shivaji ",
            "optionC": "  Sambaji ",
            "optionD": "  Shahu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMukarrab Khan with his large army attacked Sambhji Maharaj with an army of 4000. The 400 Maratha soldiers attacked so ferociously, that Mukarab Khan was taken by surprise. Sambhaji Maharaj along with Kavi Kalash was captured and taken as prisoner to Aurangzeb who killed him with utmost brutality. ",
            "keyString": "472812s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jizya was abolished by the Mughal ruler",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJizya was abolished by the third Mughal emperor Akbar, in 1564. It was finally abolished in 1579. ",
            "keyString": "472851s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true about First Anglo-Mysore War?",
            "optionA": "  First Anglo-Mysore War fought in AD 1767-69 ",
            "optionB": "  Hyder Ali defeated the English in the First Anglo-Mysore War ",
            "optionC": "  Treaty of Madras was the result of First Anglo-Mysore War ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above\u00a0are incorrect ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Anglo\u2013Mysore War (1766\u20131769) was a conflict in India between the Sultanate of Mysore and the East India Company. The war was instigated in part by the machinations of Asaf Jah II, the Nizam of Hyderabad, who sought to divert the company's resources from attempts to gain control of the Northern Circars. ",
            "keyString": "472867s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals __________ was administered as a department of the household",
            "optionA": "  infantry ",
            "optionB": "  cavalry ",
            "optionC": "  artillery ",
            "optionD": "  navy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Mughals artillery was administered as a department of the household. ",
            "keyString": "472882s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Mughal Emperor transferred the Mughal Capital from Agra to Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  Jahangir ",
            "optionB": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionC": "  Shahjahan ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Mughal emperor to crown Agra as capital of mughal empire, was Akbar in the year 1526. The capital of mughal empire was changed from Agra to Delhi by Shah Jahan in the year 1638. ",
            "keyString": "472894s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughal rule the Chief Minister was known as",
            "optionA": "  Diwan ",
            "optionB": "  Vakil ",
            "optionC": "  Kazi ",
            "optionD": "  Mansabdar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Diwan: The Diwan was the finance minister responsible for a collection of revenue and remittance of it to the imperial treasury. The office was sometimes combined the that of Vizier. The Diwani (revenue office) was conferred on the East India Company by Shah Alam in 1765. This greatly enhanced the power of the British in India. In later years the term Diwan was also used for the prime minister of a princely state.Vakil: The Vakil was the royal deputy. It was a post filled only twice under the seven great Mughal emperors. Other ranks were in descending order:Kazi: The Chief Kazi was an Islamic scholar & judge and the expounder of canon law.Mansabdar: The Mansabdar (lit. rank holder) was the lowest grade of an official. They were divided into three functions: military, clerical and theological.",
            "keyString": "512337s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the king who invaded Delhi and plundered the Kohinoor diamond __________",
            "optionA": "  Nadir Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Firuz Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Mohammed Shah ",
            "optionD": "  Mohammed Ghori ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNadir Shah of Iran invaded India in 1739 and took with him famous Mughal peacock throne and kohinoor diamond in the battle of Karnal. ",
            "keyString": "512370s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal period Polaj was the",
            "optionA": "  land annually cultivated ",
            "optionB": "  land left fallow ",
            "optionC": "  land uncultivated ",
            "optionD": "  barren land ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPolaj was the ideal and best type of land throughout the empire. This land was cultivated always and was never allowed to lie fallow. ",
            "keyString": "512384s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the original name of Nur Jahan?",
            "optionA": "  Zeb-un-Nissa ",
            "optionB": "  Fatima Begum ",
            "optionC": "  Mehr-un-Nissa ",
            "optionD": "  Jahanara ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNur Jahan (born Mehr-un-Nissa) (31 May 1577 \u2013 17 December 1645) was the twentieth (and last) wife of the Mughal emperor Jahangir. ",
            "keyString": "512397s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughals have been made immortal by their achievements in the field",
            "optionA": "  Political ",
            "optionB": "  Architectural ",
            "optionC": "  Military ",
            "optionD": "  Social ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal architecture flourished in the Indian subcontinent from the 16th until the early 18th century when the Mughal Empire was at its height. The architectural style which is a unique blend of Islamic, Indian and Persian styles reached its golden age under Shah Jahan (ruled 1628-1658) who built the spectacular Taj Mahal and some other equally impressive monuments.",
            "keyString": "512408s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal empire reached its maximum territorial extent during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Jahan ",
            "optionC": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionD": "  Bahadur Shah I ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAurangzeb ruled 1658-1707 and expanded the empire to its greatest extent, shown by the heavy red line on the map. ",
            "keyString": "549178s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following became a member of the \"Din-i-Ilahi\"?",
            "optionA": "  Todarmal ",
            "optionB": "  Raja Birbal ",
            "optionC": "  Raja Man Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Tansen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe theory of Din-i-Ilahi was introduced by Mughal Emperor Akbar. It is based on Monotheism(believe in one God).(Chief priest : Abul Fazal).The first initiated disciples of Din-i-ilahi during emperor Akbar the Great's time included Birbal, Prince Salim and Abul-Fazl ibn Mubarak. ",
            "keyString": "549216s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Muslim mosque situated where a hair of pagamber Mohammad Sahed has been preserved",
            "optionA": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionC": "  Srinagar ",
            "optionD": "  Mecca ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Hazratbal Shrine (Urdu, Kashmiri:literally \"Majestic Place\"), is a Muslim shrine in Hazratbal, Srinagar, Jammu & Kashmir, India. It contains a relic, the Moi-e-Muqqadas, believed by many Muslims of Kashmir to be a hair of the Islamic prophet Muhammad. ",
            "keyString": "549234s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Mughals the Commander-in-Chief of the Army was",
            "optionA": "  The crown prince ",
            "optionB": "  Mansabdar ",
            "optionC": "  Emperor ",
            "optionD": "  Zamindar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommander-in-Chief, Mughal emperor. The Army of the Mughal Empire was the force by which the Mughal emperors established their empire in the 15th century and expanded it to its greatest extent at the beginning of the 18th century. ",
            "keyString": "549249s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Persian ruler who besieged Qandhar in Jahangir's reign was",
            "optionA": "  Shah Muhammad ",
            "optionB": "  Shah Parvez ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Abbas ",
            "optionD": "  Shah Raza ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Persian ruler who besieged Qandhar in Jahangir's reign was Shah Abbas. ",
            "keyString": "549262s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who constructed Humayun's tomb in Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Akbar ",
            "optionC": "  Haji Begum ",
            "optionD": "  Humayun ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tomb of Humayun was built by the orders of Humayun's first wife and chief consort, Empress Bega Begum (also known as Haji Begum). The construction began in 1565, nine years after his death, and completed in 1572 AD at a cost of 1.5 million ruppees at the time. ",
            "keyString": "586409s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun had to run away from India after he was defeated in the battle of",
            "optionA": "  Panipat ",
            "optionB": "  Ghagra ",
            "optionC": "  Khanwa ",
            "optionD": "  Kannauj ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHumayun was defeated in the battle of kannauj by Shershah Suri (1540). After this battle Sher Shah Suri forced him out of India. ",
            "keyString": "586444s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whom did Akbar defeat in the 2nd battle of Panipat in 1556?",
            "optionA": "  Genghis Khan ",
            "optionB": "  Nadir Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Hemu Vikramaditya ",
            "optionD": "  Bajirao-I ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Second Battle of Panipat was fought on November 5, 1556, between the forces of Hem Chandra Vikramaditya, the king at Delhi and forces of Emperor Akbar. ",
            "keyString": "586458s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar suppressed the rebellion of Abdullah Khan, the Governor of",
            "optionA": "  Mewar ",
            "optionB": "  Malwa ",
            "optionC": "  Meerut ",
            "optionD": "  Mankat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar appointed Abdullah Khan as the governor of Malwa with his headquarters at Mandu. Akbar suppressed the rebellion of Abdullah Khan, the Governor of Malwa. ",
            "keyString": "586471s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Akbar married a bride from",
            "optionA": "  Bikaner ",
            "optionB": "  Jaisalmer ",
            "optionC": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionD": "  Udaipur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAkbar married a bride from Udaipur. ",
            "keyString": "586484s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the first to make use of artillery in warfare in medieval India?",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "optionC": "  Sher Shah Suri ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabur was the first to make use of artillery and gunpowder fire arms in warfare during the first Battle of Panipat in 1526.",
            "keyString": "623039s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal rule in India tobacco was first cultivated in",
            "optionA": "  Madras ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTobacco manufacture can scarcely have started in India during Akbar's reign. Firstly in the province of Gujarat, where the leaf was obtainable in the 1613. ",
            "keyString": "623073s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second Battle of Panipat was fought between",
            "optionA": "  Akbar and Hemu ",
            "optionB": "  Rajputs and Mughals ",
            "optionC": "  Babur and Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "optionD": "  Sikander and Adilshah ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Second Battle of Panipat was fought between the forces of Samrat Hem Chandra Vikramaditya, popularly called Hemu, the Hindu king who was ruling North India from Delhi, and the army of Akbar, on November 5, 1556. It was a decisive victory for Akbar's generals Khan Zaman I and Bairam Khan. ",
            "keyString": "623087s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important feature of the Mughal building was the",
            "optionA": "  Dome ",
            "optionB": "  Arch ",
            "optionC": "  The narrow columns ",
            "optionD": "  Corbel brackets ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important features of the Mughal monuments in India are the bulbous domes with constricted necks, the slender minarets with cupolas at the four corners, large halls, massive vaulted gateways and delicate ornamentation. Red Sandstone was amply used in Mughal monuments. ",
            "keyString": "623099s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Mughal rule, excellent cotton goods were woven in which one of the following centres?",
            "optionA": "  Agra ",
            "optionB": "  Surat ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Calcutta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring Mughal rule, excellent cotton goods were woven in Agra. The manufacture of cotton cloth was the principal industry. ",
            "keyString": "623111s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Chittor was captured by Akbar (1558), the Rana of Mewar was",
            "optionA": "  Rana Udai Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Rana Pratap ",
            "optionC": "  Rana Kumbha ",
            "optionD": "  Rana Amar Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Chittor was captured by Akbar (1558), the Rana of Mewar was Rana Udai Singh. ",
            "keyString": "661435s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When Babur invaded India in 1525, Humayun was the Governor of",
            "optionA": "  Kabul ",
            "optionB": "  Fargana ",
            "optionC": "  Badakhshan ",
            "optionD": "  Herat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBabar set out on his final invasion of India in November, 1525. His eldest son, Humayun, brought a contingent from Badakhshan, and Khwaja Kalan, trustiest of generals, led the troops of Ghazni. ",
            "keyString": "661468s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Baburnama was written by",
            "optionA": "  Humayun ",
            "optionB": "  Babur ",
            "optionC": "  Abul Fazl ",
            "optionD": "  Akbar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"Memoirs of Babur\" or Baburnama are the work of the great-great-great-grandson of Timur (Tamerlane), Zahiruddin Muhammad Babur (1483-1530). ",
            "keyString": "661483s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Humayun (1530-1540 AD) was the ruler of which dynasty?",
            "optionA": "  Nanda ",
            "optionB": "  Mughal ",
            "optionC": "  Maurya ",
            "optionD": "  Haryanka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNasir-ud-Din Mu\u1e25ammad, better known by his regional name, Humayun, was the second emperor of the Mughal Empire, who ruled over territory in what is now Afghanistan, Pakistan, Northern India and Bangladesh from 1530\u20131540 and again from 1555\u20131556.",
            "keyString": "661495s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Defeated Humayun in the Battle of Kannauj (1540) also constructed the Purana Qila of New Delhi",
            "optionA": "  Adil Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Malik Kafur ",
            "optionC": "  Bin-Kasim ",
            "optionD": "  Sher Shah Suri ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 26 June 1539, Sher Khan faced Humayun in the Battle of Chausa and defeated him. Assuming the title Farid al-Din Sher Shah, he defeated Humayun once again at Kannauj in May 1540 and forced him out of India. He also constructed the Purana Qila of New Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "661507s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal subdued the Pathans by following the policy of",
            "optionA": "  Annexation ",
            "optionB": "  Association ",
            "optionC": "  Divide and rule ",
            "optionD": "  Co-existence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy 1675 A.D. Mughal authority was reestablished in the north-western frontier. The Pathan tribes were finally subdued by the policy of divide and rule. ",
            "keyString": "698794s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Mughal Prince who was well-versed in Arabic, Persian and Sanakrit?",
            "optionA": "  Prince Akbar ",
            "optionB": "  Prince Salim ",
            "optionC": "  Prince Sulaiman Shukoh ",
            "optionD": "  Prince Dara Shukoh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrince Dara Shukoh was the Mughal Prince who was well-versed in Arabic, Persian and Sanskrit. ",
            "keyString": "698832s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1739, who defeated the Mughal army at the Battle of Karnal?",
            "optionA": "  Nader Shah ",
            "optionB": "  Genghis Khan ",
            "optionC": "  Hemu Vikramaclitya ",
            "optionD": "  Bajirao-I ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmperor Nader Shah, the Shah of Persia (1736\u201347) and the founder of the Afsharid dynasty of Persia, invaded the Mughal Empire, eventually attacking Delhi in March 1739. His army had easily defeated the Mughals at the battle at Karnal and would eventually capture the Mughal capital in the aftermath of the battle. ",
            "keyString": "698849s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced the Subsidiary Alliance System in India?",
            "optionA": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Ripan ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Wellesley ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe doctrine of subsidiary alliance was introduced by Lord Wellesley, British Governor-General in India from 1798 to 1805. Early in his governorship Wellesley adopted a policy of non-intervention in the princely states, but he later adopted the policy of forming subsidiary alliances. ",
            "keyString": "698863s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vasco da Gama a sailor belongs to __________.",
            "optionA": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionB": "  American ",
            "optionC": "  German ",
            "optionD": "  South American ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVasco da Gama (1469 or 1469-December 24, 1524) was a Portuguese sailor. He was the first European who went to India through the Cape of Good Hope, the southern end of Africa in Cape Town. He went to India three times by ship. He was born in Sines, Portugal. ",
            "keyString": "698875s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mughal presence in the Red fort was ceased by",
            "optionA": "  Robert Clive ",
            "optionB": "  Lord hording ",
            "optionC": "  Heuroz ",
            "optionD": "  John Nicholsan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal presence in the Red fort was ceased by East India Company under Commander John Nicholsan with the fall of Bahadur Shah Zafar during the Revolt of 1857. ",
            "keyString": "737608s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughal Emperor who discouraged 'Sati' was",
            "optionA": "  Babur ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun ",
            "optionC": "  Akbar ",
            "optionD": "  Jehangir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSati were supposed to be voluntary. Since it was offensive to the sentiments of the Mughals, its rulers such as Akbar the Great explicitly banned involuntary sati. On a superficial level, therefore, most these women were not resistant to committing sati at all. ",
            "keyString": "737643s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Mughal Emperors wrote their own autobigraphies?",
            "optionA": "  Shah Alam and Farukh Siyar ",
            "optionB": "  Babur and Jahangir ",
            "optionC": "  Jahangir and Shah Jahan ",
            "optionD": "  Akbr and Aurangzeb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughal Emperor Babur wrote his autobiography Baburnama. (Tuzk-e-Babri) in Chapatai Language and Mughal Emperor Jahangir wrote autobiography Tuzuk-e-Jahangiri which is written in Persian Language.",
            "keyString": "737661s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The huge wealth of the Mughals Cell into the hands of __________ after the capture of Delhi in 1739",
            "optionA": "  Nadir Shah ",
            "optionB": "  The English ",
            "optionC": "  The French ",
            "optionD": "  The Portuguese ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmperor Nader Shah, the Shah of Persia (1736\u201347) and the founder of the Afsharid dynasty of Persia, invaded the Mughal Empire, eventually attacking Delhi in March 1739. His army had easily defeated the Mughals at the battle at Karnal and would eventually capture the Mughal capital in the aftermath of the battle. ",
            "keyString": "737674s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The court language of the Mughals was",
            "optionA": "  Urdu ",
            "optionB": "  Hindi ",
            "optionC": "  Arabic ",
            "optionD": "  Persian ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHumayun's exile in Persia established diplomatic ties between the Safavid and Mughal Courts, and led to increasing Persian cultural influence in the Mughal Empire. ",
            "keyString": "737687s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the policy of \"doctrine of lapse\"?",
            "optionA": "  States were allowed to adopt son as an heir ",
            "optionB": "  States were not allowed to adopt son as an heir ",
            "optionC": "  According to this system, every ruler in India had to accept to pay a subsidy to the British for the maintenance of British army ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis doctrine was based on the idea that in case a ruler of dependent state died childless, the right of ruling over the State reverted or 'lapsed' to the sovereign. ",
            "keyString": "776489s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the four Agnikula classes of Rajputs?",
            "optionA": "  Tomars, Pariharas, Chauhans, Pawars ",
            "optionB": "  Chandellas, Tornars, Solankis, Chauhans ",
            "optionC": "  Chandellas, Pariharas, Chauhans, Pawars ",
            "optionD": "  Pariharas, Chauhans, Pawars, Solankis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tClans that are included in the agnikula rajputs are Pariharas, Chauhans, Pawars, Solankis. ",
            "keyString": "776526s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the Mughal rule in the field of agriculture Parauti was the land",
            "optionA": "  annually cultivated ",
            "optionB": "  left fallow ",
            "optionC": "  uncultivated ",
            "optionD": "  barren land ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParauti was the land which had to be left fallow for one or two years to recoup the fertility. ",
            "keyString": "776544s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two Sayid brothers Sayid Abdullah Khan and Sayid Hussan Ali Khan (who rose to become the king makers during the later Mughal period) met their downfall during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Farrukhsiyar ",
            "optionB": "  Rafi-ud-DaIjat ",
            "optionC": "  Rafi-ud-Daula ",
            "optionD": "  Muhammad Shah ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo Sayyid brothers Sayyid Abdullah Khan and Shahid Hassan Ali Khan (who rose to become the king makers during the later Mughal period) met their downfall during the reign of Muhammad Shah. ",
            "keyString": "776558s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "I. Hawkins was the first Englishman to visit Jahangir's court\nII. Hawkins was called by the name of English Khan, by Jahangir\nWhich of the above statement (s) is/are correct related to Hawkins?",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II are incorrect ",
            "optionC": "  Only I is correct ",
            "optionD": "  Only II is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHawkins was the first Englishman to visit Jahangir's court. Hawkins was called by the name of English Khan, by Jahangir. This English Khan was able to persuade the emperor to grant a commission for an English factory at Surat but under the Pressure of the Portuguese Viceroy, the grant was withdrawn. ",
            "keyString": "776571s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arab merchant, Suleiman, came to India in 9th century in the kingdom of",
            "optionA": "  Vijaysena of Sena dynasty ",
            "optionB": "  Mihira Bhoja of Prathihara dynasty ",
            "optionC": "  Gopala of the Pala dynasty ",
            "optionD": "  Dantidurga of Rashtrakuta dynasty ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArab merchant, Suleiman, came to India in 9th century in the kingdom was Mihira Bhoja of Prathihara dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "813364s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Peacock Throne of Shah Jahan was taken away in 1739 by",
            "optionA": "  Afghan invader Ahmed Shah Abdali ",
            "optionB": "  Persian invader Nadir Shah ",
            "optionC": "  Mongol invader Chengiz Khan ",
            "optionD": "  British East India Company ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1739, Persian invader Nadir Shah plundered and looted Delhi,and the Peacock throne was taken away along with other spoils. It was believed that after Nadir Shah\u2019s death the Peacock throne was broken down and damaged. ",
            "keyString": "813398s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these is not correctly matched regarding the reign of Shahjahan?",
            "optionA": "  Chintamani - Hindi poet ",
            "optionB": "  Jagannath Pandit - Poet laureate ",
            "optionC": "  Asaf Khan - Wazir ",
            "optionD": "  Sunder Das - Singer ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSunder Das was a poet. ",
            "keyString": "813412s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement (s) related to the Zeb-un-nisa\nI. Zeb-un-nisa chose to live voluntarily with Shah Jahan and later was awarded great honour by Aurangzeb.\nII. Zeb-un-nisa was the sister of Shah Jahan.",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  Both I and II are incorrect ",
            "optionC": "  Only I is correct ",
            "optionD": "  Only II is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tZeb-un-nisa was a Mughal princess, the eldest child of Emperor Aurangzeb and his chief consort Dilras Banu Begum. Zeb-un-nisa chose to live voluntarily with Shah Jahan and later was awarded great honour by Aurangzeb. ",
            "keyString": "813424s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bahadur Shah was the",
            "optionA": "  Last ruler of the Lodis ",
            "optionB": "  Successor of Sher Shah Suri ",
            "optionC": "  Last Mughal ruler ",
            "optionD": "  Successor of the Maratha ruler Shivaji ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMirza Abu Zafar Siraj-ud-din Muhammad Bahadur Shah Zafar was the last Mughal emperor. He was the second son of and became the successor to his father, Akbar II, upon his death on 28 September 1837. ",
            "keyString": "813439s31m49h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}